<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Twilight Landscapes Blog - Observatory Build</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/observatory-build.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00-10:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>Backyard Observatory - Use Cases</title><link href="/2021-10-12-observatory03-use-cases.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-10-12:/2021-10-12-observatory03-use-cases.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven't written about the observatory plans in a while.  Several things have come up which delayed a start on construction, but I'm getting back to it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What will this observatory be used for?  I had to consider what I wanted to get out of this before I could …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven't written about the observatory plans in a while.  Several things have come up which delayed a start on construction, but I'm getting back to it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What will this observatory be used for?  I had to consider what I wanted to get out of this before I could really get in to designing it.  One thing I knew from the start was that I wanted to plan for making it completely remotely controlled and eventually totally robotic.  A good fraction of clear skies come in the mornings here when I'm asleep and I wanted to take advantage of those.  My "day job" as a Staff Astronomer means I have a pretty variable sleeping schedule, but instead of this making it easier for me to justify staying up all night, it makes me cherish the times when I can get a full night's sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next question is whether I want to accomodate eyepiece viewing.  This actually has a big impact on the footprint of the observatory.  If the goal is imaging only, then the enclosure has to be big enough to contain the swing area of the mount and telescope with a camera attached.  If you want a human in there looking through an eyepiece, you need additional room on all sides for them to walk and also for an observing chair to fit so they can get to the eyepiece comfortably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had initially decided that the goal was remote or robotic imaging only with no eyepiece viewing no accommodations for an observer.  I've done some astrophotography in the past, but always by taking my gear out to a dark site.  This really limited how much imaging I did though.  Much of my time under dark skies involved tweaking and troubleshooting equipment that was set up and taken down each night, so new issues seemed to crop up all the time.  I eventually decided that to do imaging well, I really needed a permanent setup and I put those activities on hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got close to breaking ground on a small (7 foot square) imaging-only observatory before some conversations with other observatory owners and some more thinking made me decide to go with something bigger.  I still expect that I will primarily use this with a camera on the telescope, but I'd like the option of doing eyepiece observing.  In addition, having room for a person around the telescope makes any installation and troubleshooting of equipment easier and it means I'll have plenty of room to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also think I'll take more advantage of the skies here at home if I can do eyepiece observing at a moment's notice.  Without the overhead of setup time, I think I'll do a bit more planetary and lunar observing when it isn't new moon as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still not sure how much "pretty picture" imaging I'll end up doing.  I really enjoy the data collection aspects of imaging and I do enjoy working with the equipment.  I haven't found the image processing very satisfying though.  It seems that the really good imagers out there get a lot of satisfaction out of the processing steps to take the reduced data and make a really aesthetically beautiful image.  I'm not sure I have the skills or patience to do that sort of image processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there is a whole other area where having this observatory does interest me a great deal and that is for science.  Just doing some straightforward photometric monitoring projects would be interesting.  I'm also intrigued by a new class of detectors based on InGaS which are starting to come down in price.  These detectors are sensitive in the near-infrared out to a wavelength of almost 1.5 microns.  At the moment, they are too expensive, but in the future I hope to be able to do near-IR photometry which is a field that is not crowded right now due to the technical challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I'd love to be able to do some spectroscopic monitoring projects.  Most of the observations at the observatory where I work are spectroscopic measurements and it is still only a small subset of amateur astronomers who are exploring this -- though there are growing numbers of them and there are now several commercially available spectrographs for amateurs.  Once the observatory is in place and operational, I hope to buy a spectrograph and add a scope dedicated to spectroscopy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Update&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One quick update on actual progress on building the observatory: I've just received a shipment of lumber and other building materials, so things should start moving quickly now.  More to come in future articles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lumber to start the observatory build arrives and is stacked in my garage." src="images/Observatory_Lumber_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lumber to start the observatory build arrives and is stacked in my garage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Observatory Design"></category></entry><entry><title>Backyard Observatory - Weather</title><link href="/observatory02-weather.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-17T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-04-17T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-04-17:/observatory02-weather.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the 5 years I've lived in this house, I've found that I have a decent amount of clear skies.  It's not the summit of Maunakea, but it is enough to be useful.  On the other hand, wind and blowing rain will likely be a major problem for an observatory …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the 5 years I've lived in this house, I've found that I have a decent amount of clear skies.  It's not the summit of Maunakea, but it is enough to be useful.  On the other hand, wind and blowing rain will likely be a major problem for an observatory.  I live on the "dry side" of the town of Waimea on the Big Island of Hawaii.  Waimea sits in the saddle between Maunakea and Kohala, so the prevailing trade winds are often funneled through this area and blow steadily.  Winds routinely average 20 mph with gusts to 30+ mph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The banner photo above looks out of the back of my property toward the Kohalas.  You can see the influence of the wind on the tree line to the left, but you can also see I have no development on that side of the house which keeps the skies dark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to wind shaking the telescope and blurring the image, the winds often carry misty rain.  As the trade winds blow moisture up against the mountain slopes, it precipitates out as rain.  This is why Hilo and the Hamakua coast are so lush and green.  As a result, the leeward areas of Kawaihae and Waikoloa Village are very dry.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Landsat image of the Big Island" src="images/Hawaii_Landsat.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Landsat image of the Big Island (courtesy of NOAA/NASA) with labels added by me indicating the mountains on the island and the town of Waimea where I live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Landsat image above shows this beautifully.  The dark green areas show where there is heavy rainfall and lush vegetation.  Rainfall in the Kohala mountains has carved out dramatic valleys on the windward side.  My house lies West of Waimea near where the slopes of Maunakea and Kohala meet and right at the boundary between the green and brown areas in the Landsat image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mist and rain on the wet side of the mountains can be carried by the wind over to where I am even when it is clear overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Kohala Mountains" src="images/IMG_5030.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kohala Mountains&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blowing rain means we get rainbows on an almost daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Rainbows in front of the Kohalas." src="images/IMG_5046.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rainbows in front of the Kohalas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After watching the weather here for several years I know that I get clear skies -- enough to make an observatory useful, but the problem will be that wind.  As a result, I'll have to design the observatory to handle wind and make sure it can close reliably if the wind carries rain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my first steps in planning was to install a decent weather station.  I've had an astronomy specific weather station (an AAG Cloudwatcher) with an anemometer attached to the house for a while, but that had to come down when the house was painted.  The wind readings from it were not reliable anyway thanks to where I'd mounted it on the corner of the house.  The wind readings were extreme due to the air moving over the corner of the roof.  I couldn't move the station far from the house because it needs a hardwired connection to a computer and power.  Deploying the AAG in a better spot will have to wait until the observatory is done and providing a safe space for the computer it needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I recently installed a weather station (a Davis Vantage Vue) out at the edge of the property where it would get a better measure of the wind.  The Vantage Vue has a built in solar panel, battery, and wireless communication, so positioning it reasonably far from the house becomes possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install the weather station, I used an 8 foot section of aluminum pipe that I'd bought for this process (the Davis has a built in pole mount).  I dug out a hole roughly 16 inches deep and 10 inches across and set the pole in concrete.  While the concrete set, I used a spare "surveyor's tripod" and some gaffer tape to prevent the pole from tipping over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bracing the pole for the weather station while the mortar set." src="images/IMG_5252.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bracing the pole for the weather station while the mortar set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the concrete had set, I attached the weather station, aligned it to North and I'm now getting much more reliable wind data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the full Davis weather station, I also have a BloomSky.  This is a small weather station which has only a few basic sensors, but provides a wide angle image of the sky (daytime only).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a link to my &lt;a href="https://www.weatherlink.com/bulletin/b6320138-fb92-4287-a791-8a37878d1ba3"&gt;Kamuela View&lt;/a&gt; weather station on WeatherLink (requires a free WeatherLink account to view) and my &lt;a href="https://map.bloomsky.com/weather-stations/faBiuZWsmKKlmJm0"&gt;BloomSky&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Observatory Design"></category></entry><entry><title>Backyard Observatory - Introduction</title><link href="/observatory01-intro.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-16T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-04-16T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-04-16:/observatory01-intro.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been dreaming of building a backyard observatory since I got hooked on astronomy as kid.  I remember dreaming of building a dome and putting it in the backyard of my parents house.  Building it was way beyond my capabilities at the time of course, but here I am almost …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been dreaming of building a backyard observatory since I got hooked on astronomy as kid.  I remember dreaming of building a dome and putting it in the backyard of my parents house.  Building it was way beyond my capabilities at the time of course, but here I am almost 30 years later and I'm just now feeling confident enough to embark on a similar project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I bought my current home 5 years ago, one of the things which attracted me to it was that there is a large open area to the side of the house with space and clear enough horizons for an observatory.  In addition, my house backs on to ranch land, so there are no houses on two sides of me which means I get beautiful views of the Kohalas and it helps keep the skies dark and the horizons clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While almost no residential areas are ideal for an observatory, my house is not too bad for it.  I live in a rural area without a lot of light pollution and while there is a street light at the edge of my property, I think I can live with it.  The skies are still much darker than many other places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My plan is to document the observatory build here on this blog.  I'm not sure how long the whole process will take, but I want a record of it and I'm hoping that making this public will motivate me to push through any challenges on the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll make several posts here documenting some of my planning process and then (hopefully) move on to discussing the actual build.  Next up will be discussing the local weather and how that will affect my plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see all articles in this series, look at articles listed under the &lt;a href="tag/observatory-build"&gt;Observatory Build&lt;/a&gt; tag.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Observatory Design"></category></entry></feed>