<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Twilight Landscapes Blog - Observatory Build</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/observatory-build.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2021-10-23T00:00:00-10:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>Backyard Observatory - Construction Begins</title><link href="/observatory05-construction-begins.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-10-23T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-10-23:/observatory05-construction-begins.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're finally to the point where I can start the build.  I'd ordered lumber and other supplies from the local building supply company. They &lt;a href="observatory03-use-cases"&gt;arrived&lt;/a&gt; on a truck and were forklifted in to my garage.  Sadly, that was a busy week at work for me, so I didn't get the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're finally to the point where I can start the build.  I'd ordered lumber and other supplies from the local building supply company. They &lt;a href="observatory03-use-cases"&gt;arrived&lt;/a&gt; on a truck and were forklifted in to my garage.  Sadly, that was a busy week at work for me, so I didn't get the build started right away.  The sum total of my accomplishments for the first 5 days was to invert the stack of lumber as the pieces I'd need first were near the bottom (of course).  When the weekend arrived, I could get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Weekend 1&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The build begins with the floor.  I'm following the general outline of the Backyard Observatories CJE1 plans, but making a few modifications.  I started by digging out six holes for the posts on which the floor rests and the larger central hole for the pier.  I dug them out by hand with a post hole digger (actually this was done quite a while before lumber arrived).  With the rocky soil I have, this was a lot of work, but doable by just spending an hour or so on each of a few evenings after work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the pier, I read &lt;a href="https://www.cloudynights.com/topic/652025-pier-engineering/"&gt;this thread&lt;/a&gt; on Cloud Nights for advice.  I don't have a frost line to worry about, so the six support post holes are somewhere around 16-20 inches deep.  That should give plenty of support.  For the pier, I went as deep as I reasonably could, which turns out to be just over 3 feet.  Below that, my post hole digger won't reach very well.  The hole starts at the top at around 12-14 inches diameter, but tapers significantly toward the bottom where a few stubborn rocks prevented me from digging any more out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not use the same strategy in the CJE1 plans to square up the floor.  Their plans drop a 4x6 post vertically in each hole (to be cemented in once square), connect them together with rim boards and joists while tweaking the dimensions to make it square.  I ended up not being able to get the right ground treatment 4x6 wood, so I'll have to use post bases embedded in the concrete to connect the wooden post to the ground.  I opted to use a style of post bases which are embedded in the concrete as it sets (rather than ones drilled in later).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took two days to work out exactly how to square things up properly.  The first attempt was using some stands I rigged up out of scrap lumber and clamps to place the outer frame, but with the high winds I get here (20 mph sustained and 30-40 mpg gusts on the weekend I was doing this) kept knocking over my stands and the uneven ground made it hard to mate adjacent pieces properly.  Instead I decided to eyeball the first post position and set it in concrete, then use that as a secure and stable reference and go from there.  This worked much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The first corner post of the observatory in place." src="images/Observatory/first_post.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first corner post of the observatory in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With one post in place (at the high corner), I could clamp up two 2x8s cut to length which will outline the floor, and level them by clamping them to stands made from scrap lumber.  Now I have the correct length to the next corner posts, I just need to make sure the angle is square.  I measured out a 3-4-5 foot triangle around the corner post, adjusted the angle until the measurements came together properly, and screwed down a 2x4 on the hypotenuse to lock in the angle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The first corner measured out for square and clamped in place." src="images/Observatory/first_corner.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first corner measured out for square and clamped in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I could pour concrete in the next two corner holes and place the post bases in them -- holding them in place relative to the 2x8s with some clamps and more scrap lumber.  It may not look like much, but a day of work and I have 3 corner posts positioned.  I'm waiting for the concrete to set before installing the posts and placing weight on them, so the rim boards are still help up by clamps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I may have over sized the post holes since they will no longer contain the 4x6s, it took 10 60 lb. bags of concrete to get all 3 holes done.  I was expecting to use half that much and my back can feel it.  I'm mixing the concrete by hand which is hard work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most satisfying bit was measuring out the diagonal and finding out that I'd hit the expected distance based only on my 3-4-5 triangle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Weekend 2&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next round of work really focussed on one big day.  A friend of mine, Ben, had access to a concrete mixer and after mixing 600 lbs. of concrete by hand the week before, I was ready for the help.  I'm glad I took the time to do those first three corners by hand since I wanted to make sure they were square, but mixing and puring the concrete for the last corner and the pier by hand, would have been a bit too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We checked the position of the final hole and used it to get our routine in place for mixing the concrete.  A quick break while it set, then we went back out, set up scrap wood as braces for the central pier, trying to keep the desired target height, position, and make it level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concrete pour on the pier went pretty well.  The rebar cage needed a little manual jiggling as it settled a bit too deep after we started pouring concrete over it, but we got it in to position just in time.  The concrete was filled to near the top of the sonotube and I positioned the jig holding the J-bolts for the pier using my daytime reference for North which was a conveniently positioned tree (or perhaps inconvieniently positioned as I won't see Polaris directly from inside the observatory).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following day was mostly a day of rest for me, but I did go out and nail in the end joist to close in the square base -- we'd kept it open to allow for wheelbarrow access.  The base is in and (mostly) square.  I think there's about 1/4-3/8" of inconsistency with all the measurements, but it is as close to square as I could make it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The outside frame of the floor and the pier are in place. " src="images/Observatory/floor_frame.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outside frame of the floor and the pier are in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next steps are to finalize the floor by adding some lag bolts for added strength, concrete in the last two post bases, and then add the internal joists.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Observatory Design"></category></entry><entry><title>Backyard Observatory - Deciding on the Basic Layout</title><link href="/observatory04-basic-layout.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-19T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-10-19T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-10-19:/observatory04-basic-layout.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I got closer to breaking ground on this observatory a few choices about design had to be made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background Research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last few years, I've looked at a number of sources for information on observatory builds for inspiration.  This includes the books "Building a Roll-Off Roof or Dome …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I got closer to breaking ground on this observatory a few choices about design had to be made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background Research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last few years, I've looked at a number of sources for information on observatory builds for inspiration.  This includes the books "Building a Roll-Off Roof or Dome Observatory" by John Stephen Hicks, "Setting up a Small Observatory" by David Arditti (both part of Patrick Moore's Practical Astronomy Series), the "How to Build an Observatory" pamphlet from &lt;a href="http://outsideology.com"&gt;Outsideology&lt;/a&gt;, and the build plans from both &lt;a href="https://www.skyshed.com"&gt;SkyShed&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://backyardobservatories.com"&gt;Backyard Observatories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dome or Roll Off Roof?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in my earlier discussion of the &lt;a href="observatory02-weather"&gt;weather&lt;/a&gt;, I expect wind will be a major factor for the telescope unless the observatory can provide significant protection.  For this reason, I'd thought about using a dome style observatory early on and I'd looked at some of the commercial options available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I decided against using a dome.  I'm not really a big fan of domes for small observatories.  It seems like many people build them for the look.  I also worry about the chimney effect of having any heat in the structure funnel out through the dome slit in front of your telescope and impact the seeing.  Finally, I prefer the simplicity of a roll off roof.  The control system and electronics are far simpler because there's no need to bridge electricity across to the rotating part of the dome in order to operate the shutter.  While this is not too difficult these days (during my time as a postdoc I built a pair of robotic domed observatories), I wanted to keep my own build as simple as possible.  As a result, I decided that I was willing to live with the lesser wind protection of a roll off roof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, I'll keep the walls relatively high to shield the telescope from wind.  This actually provides another advantage: the telescope will be able to slew around inside the closed observatory.  This is important because if the roof can not hit the telescope at any position, then it will be able to close without waiting for the telescope to park.  This is really nice because if there is a problem with the telescope mount or computer control of the mount, you may not be able to close the roof in case of bad weather.  That entire class of problem goes away if you can open and close the roof without worrying about the telescope's position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, one can connect the weather station to the roof controller directly and have the weather station trigger a close without going through the control software on the computer.  This eliminates another entire class of failure: if the computer has crashed, the system will still close in the event of bad weather.  It will be much easier for me to sleep while the system is in operation if this is the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concrete Slab or Deck Flooring?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question was always a relatively easy one for me.  Concrete is a thermal mass which would radiate heat away during the night and cause seeing issues.  The big research telescopes are built on concrete foundations, but they are also air conditioned during the day so that the interior (including the concrete flooring) is kept at nighttime temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, I doubt this would have a big negative effect on a small observatory like the one I have in mind.  In addition, while being on the &lt;a href="observatory02-weather"&gt;"dry side" of Waimea&lt;/a&gt; means I have some clear skies, it also means that I'm on the lee side of a mountain range, so I don't expect great seeing on a typical night.  Just going out and watching the twinkling of stars by eye, I can tell there are a number of nights with quite poor seeing that I'll be dealing with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I didn't want to deal with arranging for a cement truck and pouring a large cement pad.  It will likely be more work to build footings and a deck, but I prefer that solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dimensions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How big should this be?  To get a starting idea, I set up a couple of my telescopes and measured the rough swing area to get an idea of how much clearance I'd need.  My Stellarvue SVX152 refractor with an eyepiece and diagonal on a G-11 mount needs about a 3 foot radius to avoid collisions.  It'll need additional space to accomodate an observer.  Call that an extra 2 feet radially at minimum and you get about a 5 foot radius.  My 16 inch f/4.5 TeleKit dobsonian also has a swing radius of about 5 feet.  While I don't expect to set up the dob in the observatory, it is a nice reference to have in case I change my mind.  Fortunately, with a dob, the observer stands next to the eyepiece and not behind it, so I don't need much extra space to accomodate the observer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given those numbers, I'm looking at something at least 10 foot square.  Given that I'm now building a bit bigger (both in footprint and height) than the small, imaging only enclosure I'd originally envisioned.  I think I'm going to base my build on one of the pre-existing plans I've purchased rather than design my own from scratch.  I've heard good things about both &lt;a href="https://www.skyshed.com"&gt;SkyShed&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://backyardobservatories.com"&gt;Backyard Observatories&lt;/a&gt; (BYO), but the CJE1 plans I bought from BYO are a bit roomier.  The largest SkyShed in the plans is 10x12 feet and the BYO is 11.5 x 11.5 feet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually considered going even larger in order to accomodate more storage and even space for a small work area and was looking at the BYO CJE2 model which is 11.5 x 15.5 feet, but I decided it would be better if this plan stopped growing at some point, so I decided to stick with the CJE1.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Observatory Design"></category></entry><entry><title>Backyard Observatory - Use Cases</title><link href="/observatory03-use-cases.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-12T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-10-12:/observatory03-use-cases.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven't written about the observatory plans in a while.  Several things have come up which delayed a start on construction, but I'm getting back to it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What will this observatory be used for?  I had to consider what I wanted to get out of this before I could …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven't written about the observatory plans in a while.  Several things have come up which delayed a start on construction, but I'm getting back to it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What will this observatory be used for?  I had to consider what I wanted to get out of this before I could really get in to designing it.  One thing I knew from the start was that I wanted to plan for making it completely remotely controlled and eventually totally robotic.  A good fraction of clear skies come in the mornings here when I'm asleep and I wanted to take advantage of those.  My "day job" as a Staff Astronomer means I have a pretty variable sleeping schedule, but instead of this making it easier for me to justify staying up all night, it makes me cherish the times when I can get a full night's sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next question is whether I want to accomodate eyepiece viewing.  This actually has a big impact on the footprint of the observatory.  If the goal is imaging only, then the enclosure has to be big enough to contain the swing area of the mount and telescope with a camera attached.  If you want a human in there looking through an eyepiece, you need additional room on all sides for them to walk and also for an observing chair to fit so they can get to the eyepiece comfortably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had initially decided that the goal was remote or robotic imaging only with no eyepiece viewing no accommodations for an observer.  I've done some astrophotography in the past, but always by taking my gear out to a dark site.  This really limited how much imaging I did though.  Much of my time under dark skies involved tweaking and troubleshooting equipment that was set up and taken down each night, so new issues seemed to crop up all the time.  I eventually decided that to do imaging well, I really needed a permanent setup and I put those activities on hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got close to breaking ground on a small (7 foot square) imaging-only observatory before some conversations with other observatory owners and some more thinking made me decide to go with something bigger.  I still expect that I will primarily use this with a camera on the telescope, but I'd like the option of doing eyepiece observing.  In addition, having room for a person around the telescope makes any installation and troubleshooting of equipment easier and it means I'll have plenty of room to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also think I'll take more advantage of the skies here at home if I can do eyepiece observing at a moment's notice.  Without the overhead of setup time, I think I'll do a bit more planetary and lunar observing when it isn't new moon as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still not sure how much "pretty picture" imaging I'll end up doing.  I really enjoy the data collection aspects of imaging and I do enjoy working with the equipment.  I haven't found the image processing very satisfying though.  It seems that the really good imagers out there get a lot of satisfaction out of the processing steps to take the reduced data and make a really aesthetically beautiful image.  I'm not sure I have the skills or patience to do that sort of image processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there is a whole other area where having this observatory does interest me a great deal and that is for science.  Just doing some straightforward photometric monitoring projects would be interesting.  I'm also intrigued by a new class of detectors based on InGaS which are starting to come down in price.  These detectors are sensitive in the near-infrared out to a wavelength of almost 1.5 microns.  At the moment, they are too expensive, but in the future I hope to be able to do near-IR photometry which is a field that is not crowded right now due to the technical challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I'd love to be able to do some spectroscopic monitoring projects.  Most of the observations at the observatory where I work are spectroscopic measurements and it is still only a small subset of amateur astronomers who are exploring this -- though there are growing numbers of them and there are now several commercially available spectrographs for amateurs.  Once the observatory is in place and operational, I hope to buy a spectrograph and add a scope dedicated to spectroscopy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Update&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One quick update on actual progress on building the observatory: I've just received a shipment of lumber and other building materials, so things should start moving quickly now.  More to come in future articles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lumber to start the observatory build arrives and is stacked in my garage." src="images/Observatory/Lumber_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lumber to start the observatory build arrives and is stacked in my garage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Observatory Design"></category></entry><entry><title>Backyard Observatory - Weather</title><link href="/observatory02-weather.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-17T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-04-17T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-04-17:/observatory02-weather.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the 5 years I've lived in this house, I've found that I have a decent amount of clear skies.  It's not the summit of Maunakea, but it is enough to be useful.  On the other hand, wind and blowing rain will likely be a major problem for an observatory …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the 5 years I've lived in this house, I've found that I have a decent amount of clear skies.  It's not the summit of Maunakea, but it is enough to be useful.  On the other hand, wind and blowing rain will likely be a major problem for an observatory.  I live on the "dry side" of the town of Waimea on the Big Island of Hawaii.  Waimea sits in the saddle between Maunakea and Kohala, so the prevailing trade winds are often funneled through this area and blow steadily.  Winds routinely average 20 mph with gusts to 30+ mph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The banner photo above looks out of the back of my property toward the Kohalas.  You can see the influence of the wind on the tree line to the left, but you can also see I have no development on that side of the house which keeps the skies dark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to wind shaking the telescope and blurring the image, the winds often carry misty rain.  As the trade winds blow moisture up against the mountain slopes, it precipitates out as rain.  This is why Hilo and the Hamakua coast are so lush and green.  As a result, the leeward areas of Kawaihae and Waikoloa Village are very dry.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Landsat image of the Big Island" src="images/Observatory/Hawaii_Landsat.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Landsat image of the Big Island (courtesy of NOAA/NASA) with labels added by me indicating the mountains on the island and the town of Waimea where I live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Landsat image above shows this beautifully.  The dark green areas show where there is heavy rainfall and lush vegetation.  Rainfall in the Kohala mountains has carved out dramatic valleys on the windward side.  My house lies West of Waimea near where the slopes of Maunakea and Kohala meet and right at the boundary between the green and brown areas in the Landsat image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mist and rain on the wet side of the mountains can be carried by the wind over to where I am even when it is clear overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Kohala Mountains" src="images/Observatory/IMG_5030.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kohala Mountains&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blowing rain means we get rainbows on an almost daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Rainbows in front of the Kohalas." src="images/Observatory/IMG_5046.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rainbows in front of the Kohalas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After watching the weather here for several years I know that I get clear skies -- enough to make an observatory useful, but the problem will be that wind.  As a result, I'll have to design the observatory to handle wind and make sure it can close reliably if the wind carries rain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my first steps in planning was to install a decent weather station.  I've had an astronomy specific weather station (an AAG Cloudwatcher) with an anemometer attached to the house for a while, but that had to come down when the house was painted.  The wind readings from it were not reliable anyway thanks to where I'd mounted it on the corner of the house.  The wind readings were extreme due to the air moving over the corner of the roof.  I couldn't move the station far from the house because it needs a hardwired connection to a computer and power.  Deploying the AAG in a better spot will have to wait until the observatory is done and providing a safe space for the computer it needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I recently installed a weather station (a Davis Vantage Vue) out at the edge of the property where it would get a better measure of the wind.  The Vantage Vue has a built in solar panel, battery, and wireless communication, so positioning it reasonably far from the house becomes possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install the weather station, I used an 8 foot section of aluminum pipe that I'd bought for this process (the Davis has a built in pole mount).  I dug out a hole roughly 16 inches deep and 10 inches across and set the pole in concrete.  While the concrete set, I used a spare "surveyor's tripod" and some gaffer tape to prevent the pole from tipping over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bracing the pole for the weather station while the mortar set." src="images/Observatory/IMG_5252.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bracing the pole for the weather station while the mortar set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the concrete had set, I attached the weather station, aligned it to North and I'm now getting much more reliable wind data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the full Davis weather station, I also have a BloomSky.  This is a small weather station which has only a few basic sensors, but provides a wide angle image of the sky (daytime only).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a link to my &lt;a href="https://www.weatherlink.com/bulletin/b6320138-fb92-4287-a791-8a37878d1ba3"&gt;Kamuela View&lt;/a&gt; weather station on WeatherLink (requires a free WeatherLink account to view) and my &lt;a href="https://map.bloomsky.com/weather-stations/faBiuZWsmKKlmJm0"&gt;BloomSky&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Observatory Design"></category></entry><entry><title>Backyard Observatory - Introduction</title><link href="/observatory01-intro.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-16T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-04-16T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-04-16:/observatory01-intro.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been dreaming of building a backyard observatory since I got hooked on astronomy as kid.  I remember dreaming of building a dome and putting it in the backyard of my parents house.  Building it was way beyond my capabilities at the time of course, but here I am almost …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been dreaming of building a backyard observatory since I got hooked on astronomy as kid.  I remember dreaming of building a dome and putting it in the backyard of my parents house.  Building it was way beyond my capabilities at the time of course, but here I am almost 30 years later and I'm just now feeling confident enough to embark on a similar project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I bought my current home 5 years ago, one of the things which attracted me to it was that there is a large open area to the side of the house with space and clear enough horizons for an observatory.  In addition, my house backs on to ranch land, so there are no houses on two sides of me which means I get beautiful views of the Kohalas and it helps keep the skies dark and the horizons clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While almost no residential areas are ideal for an observatory, my house is not too bad for it.  I live in a rural area without a lot of light pollution and while there is a street light at the edge of my property, I think I can live with it.  The skies are still much darker than many other places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My plan is to document the observatory build here on this blog.  I'm not sure how long the whole process will take, but I want a record of it and I'm hoping that making this public will motivate me to push through any challenges on the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll make several posts here documenting some of my planning process and then (hopefully) move on to discussing the actual build.  Next up will be discussing the local weather and how that will affect my plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see all articles in this series, look at articles listed under the &lt;a href="tag/observatory-build"&gt;Observatory Build&lt;/a&gt; tag.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observatory Build"></category><category term="Observatory Design"></category></entry></feed>