<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Twilight Landscapes Blog - Observing Reports</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/observing-reports.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2021-06-13T00:00:00-10:00</updated><entry><title>June New Moon</title><link href="/june-2021-new-moon.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-06-13T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-06-13T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-06-13:/june-2021-new-moon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got out for two long observing sessions this new moon.  In both cases, I met up with a few local amateurs at the Maunakea "Power Station" site across the street from the VIS (Visitor Information Station).  This is a location I've used often in past years, but had stopped …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got out for two long observing sessions this new moon.  In both cases, I met up with a few local amateurs at the Maunakea "Power Station" site across the street from the VIS (Visitor Information Station).  This is a location I've used often in past years, but had stopped using in favor of sites on Mauna Loa due to increasing crowds.  Visitors to Maunakea stop at the VIS which is the end of the paved road.  Those who are not able to go to the summit of Maunakea for sunset are often directed by VIS staff to a trail up the pu'u across the road for a view toward sunset.  This observing site is a clearing along that path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can confidently say that tourists have returned to the island.  The trail past this site was a constant stream of people before and after sunset.  Even late in to the night, we had a parade of people coming down the trail with flashlights.  This is a nuisance for preserving dark adaption, but fortunately, it is concentrated around twilight.  I haven't done a public star party in a long time (thanks to the pandemic) and the telescopes definitely attract attention.  I gave passers by who asked a view of the Moon in twilight and a few folks hung around after dark for looks through the five or so telescopes which were there.  It was the first truly public star party I've done in a long time and as the pandemic (hopefully) winds down, it is something I'd like to return to doing more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal for these nights, as usual, was to explore DSOs in a chosen region of the sky.  For June, it was the constellations of Libra and Serpens.  Between the two nights, I caught every object in my list: all DSOs (other than open clusters) brighter than magnitude 12.  None of those objects, mostly small galaxies and globular clusters, stood out as new or particularly memorable.  The highlights of the list we're well known objects like M5 or M16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exploring the Eagle Nebula (M16) revealed a dark area in the center which was the famous pillars of creation.  I couldn't separate out the individual pillars, but the overall shape was wedge like corresponding to the differing heights of the pillars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;June, of course, is a time of year when the Summer Milky Way starts rising in the evening and I was able to spend a lot of time exploring old favorites in this area.  Examining the Veil Nebula at low power (57x) was a treat as always.  This is one object where a filter does help, the OIII improved the contrast enough to add some real detail (the UHC filter was less effective).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bug Nebula (NGC 6302) is a lovely planetary nebula which eschews the traditional round shape in favor of an elongated pattern with open streamers on either end giving it the look of a squashed bug leading to the name&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also looked at Barnard's Galaxy (NGC 6822), which I hadn't really appreciated before.  This is a dwarf galaxy and a member of the local group.  It is easy to miss this and dismiss it as a patch of the Milky Way, but it is far in the background.  The appearance in the eyepiece is large and diffuse, but on closer examination, it has a patchy structure, so we are resolving a bit of detail in the galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Little Gem Nebula (NGC 6818) is close to Barnard's Galaxy, so I hopped over there immediately after. The two make quite a contrast.  The galaxy is large and diffuse, while the planetary nebula is very small, compact, and bright blue.  I had to run up the power to 240x to get a good look at the planetary -- at which point a small dark center was visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, to finish off the evenings, Saturn and Jupiter were rising.  Saturn was lovely, especially on June 12 when the seeing was a bit better.  I went as high as 300x on Saturn, but spent most of the time at slightly lower power.  The colors on the planet were apparent as well as the Cassini Division and the shadow of the planet on the rings and that of the rings on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I noticed that Saturn was in Capricorn, not far from The Saturn Nebula, a planetary nebula with elongations somewhat reminiscent of the planet's shape.  The "rings" on the nebula were small, but the blue color of the nebula itself was quite apparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last highlight I hit on June 12 was the R Coronae Australis region.  I wrote about this region &lt;a href="aug-2020-perseids"&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt; and it remains one of my favorite regions of the sky for the combination of features and textures visible there:  the specked stars of the globular cluster (NGC 6723), the faint wisps of reflection nebulae (NGC 6726, 6727, and 6729), and the dusty dark voids of the dark cloud.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="VIS"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="AZ100"></category></entry><entry><title>Lunar Eclipse</title><link href="/may-2021-lunar-eclipse.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-05-26T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-05-26T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-05-26:/may-2021-lunar-eclipse.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last night's lunar eclipse was well positioned for viewing from Hawaii.  The local weather, on the other hand, was less cooperative.  I had hoped to photograph the eclipse from my back yard, but the skies had alternated between clear and completely cloudy all evening.  With about 40 minutes to go …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last night's lunar eclipse was well positioned for viewing from Hawaii.  The local weather, on the other hand, was less cooperative.  I had hoped to photograph the eclipse from my back yard, but the skies had alternated between clear and completely cloudy all evening.  With about 40 minutes to go before the partial phase started, the clouds were opaque at my house, so I hit the road looking for clear skies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I drove down to the coast.  First turning South from Kawaihae toward Hapuna Beach, but I turned around after a few miles and headed back North.  I found a pullout off the road a few miles North of Kawaihae which was clear.  Clouds were building to the East over the Kohalas, but there was a view South along the coast and the Moon was visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set up my tripod and started taking images for the time lapse sequence I was hoping to assemble.  The plan was to build a sequence of images of the Moon going in to eclipse, similar to what I'd done for a previous lunar eclipse over the Halema'uma'u vent of Kilauea Volcano (see my &lt;a href="https://twilightlandscapes.com/nightscapes-for-web"&gt;nightscapes gallery&lt;/a&gt;).  Unfortunately, the clouds over the Kohalas slowly built out and covered the Moon a few minutes before totality was set to begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="One of the last views I got of the partially eclipsed Moon before the clouds covered it at my first location." src="images/6D-7791.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The photo above is one of the last views I got of the partially eclipsed Moon before the clouds covered it at my first location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got in the car and headed South and found a hole in the clouds just a few miles away.  I quickly set up the tripod and got a few images during totality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/6D-7828.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Totality.  Imaged from the side of the Akoni Pule Highway just North of Kawaihae.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm pleased with the result, even if it wasn't what I was planning.  The Milky Way, clouds illuminated by lights from Kawaihae, and the Moon make for some nice drama in the skies.  The random tree in the foreground works to give it some depth as well.  I've been unable to build a good HDR version of the image above, partially because I did not get the full set of bracketed exposures I would have liked thanks to the last minute move.  I didn't reach this location until totality was already well under way and I was rushing to get a few images before it ended.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Lunar Eclipse"></category></entry><entry><title>May New Moon</title><link href="/may-2021-new-moon.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-05-17T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-05-17T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-05-17:/may-2021-new-moon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently had a very special opportunity to spend a week at a house owned by some friends of mine.  They occasionally rent this house out as a vacation home, as it is located in a gorgeous area with sweeping views of the Kona and Kohala Coast.  It has several …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently had a very special opportunity to spend a week at a house owned by some friends of mine.  They occasionally rent this house out as a vacation home, as it is located in a gorgeous area with sweeping views of the Kona and Kohala Coast.  It has several luxury amenities such as a pool, a hot tub, and ... an observatory. :)  It is called Hale Lalani Hoku, or Home of the Milky Way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The house belongs to Marj and Roland Christen who own &lt;a href="https://www.astro-physics.com"&gt;AstroPhysics&lt;/a&gt;, a company that makes high end telescopes and mounts.  The roll off roof observatory contains a beautiful Starfire 175mm refractor on an AP1600GTO mount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did some eyepiece observing on several nights in sessions of varying lengths.  In the first session, I was curious to see how this site near the coast compared to my more typical observing sites up at high elevation in the saddle between the mountains of Maunakea and Mauna Loa.  In principle, the costal site should be somewhat less transparent thanks to additional atmosphere and humidity.  I went through a list of galaxies in Corvus (which was high in the sky at the time) which I'd viewed in my 152mm Stellarvue Refractor and compared them to the views in the 175mm Starfire.  The views in the Starfire were a bit brighter, just as one would expect from an increase in aperture.  Clearly the site was up to the task of finding faint fuzzies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I measured the sky brightness to be about 21.57 magnitudes per square arcsecond (mpas).  This is just about 0.10 mpas brighter than what I measure with the same device up in the saddle area, so it was nearly indistinguishable to the naked eye.  One thing that was significantly different was the temperature -- about 73 degrees F at 11:30 PM.  That's probably 25-30 degrees warmer than my high elevation sites would be at the same time of year.  That's a pretty amazing perk of low elevation sites here on the island if they are truly dark like this one is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next session, I explored the Coma cluster of galaxies for the first time.  I centered the telescope on NGC 4889, an 11th magnitude galaxy and one of the brightest in the cluster.  With only small telescope moves, I was able to identify 14 galaxies in an area just over half a degree across.  I also observed a number of brighter objects with no particular plan, choosing mostly based on a whim in the moment.  The seeing was not great this night, so it was mostly galaxies and other DSOs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the third session, I spent some time in and around the large face on galaxy M101.  I was able to clearly identify 3 cataloged nebulae/star clusters in the arms of the galaxy (NGC 5450, 5461, 5461) and other features in the arms were visible.  I also tracked down four small galaxies in the vicinity (NGC 5485, 5473, 5474, and 5422).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the observatory, the naked eye stargazing was wonderful.  The house looks over the Kohala coast and we had a number of gorgeous sunsets with a crescent moon setting shortly after the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The crescent Moon setting over the Pacific ocean while Venus is visible peeking out between the clouds below the Moon.  Mercury (above and slightly to the right of the Moon) and Mars (near the top of the frame) are also visible." src="images/6D-7638.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The photo above shows the crescent Moon setting over the Pacific ocean while Venus is visible peeking out between the clouds below the Moon.  Mercury (above and slightly to the right of the Moon) and Mars (near the top of the frame) are also visible.  The constellations of Auriga (right) and Orion (left) are visible as well as Aldebaran, the brightest star in Taurus, setting to the left of the Moon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The same image as above, but with labels for planets, constellations, and bright stars." src="images/6D-7638_labeled.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same image as above, but with labels for planets, constellations, and bright stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Hale Lalani Hoku"></category></entry><entry><title>March Last Quarter</title><link href="/mar-2021-last-quarter.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-03-04T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-03-04T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-03-04:/mar-2021-last-quarter.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got out for a short, mid-week observing session to take advantage of the last quarter moon last night.  I drove up to one the the pullouts on the Mauna Loa access road at about the 7,300 foot elevation level.  I stayed out for less than two hours of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got out for a short, mid-week observing session to take advantage of the last quarter moon last night.  I drove up to one the the pullouts on the Mauna Loa access road at about the 7,300 foot elevation level.  I stayed out for less than two hours of full darkness, but it was a lovely night anyway.  It was quiet (at first) with no wind.  At sunset there was a haze layer above me, possibly vog, which I could see as very thin, patchy "clouds" and the sunset colors were a bit washed out due to the scattering.  Once it was dark though, the effects were minimal and there were no thick clouds from the inversion layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started the night early, just after the end of civil twilight by looking at Zeta Cancri.  This had been described in a recent &lt;a href="https://www.cloudynights.com/articles/cat/column/phil-harrington-s/cosmic-challenge-zeta-ζ-cancri-r3286"&gt;Cosmic Challenge&lt;/a&gt; article by Phil Harrington on Cloudy Nights.  The timing was good as the seeing was excellent to start the night.  My notes describe Zeta Cancri as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lovely trio in my 5mm Pentax XW eyepiece.  The close pair is nicely surrounded by airy rings.  Moving to the 2-4mm Nagler Zoom eyepiece at 3mm reveals the dark gap between the close pair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on, I tried to look for Sirius B (since the seeing seemed to be good on Zeta Cancri), but it was tough in the glare of Sirius A.  I actually was able to see it far better in the lower power 5mm XW eyepiece than in the 2-4mm Nagler Zoom eyepiece.  Sirius B was a small, faint star following Sirius A almost hidden in the glare of the brighter star.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent most of the remainder of the night finishing out my observing list for the constellation of Eridanus.  Almost all targets were faint galaxies and some were quite challenging because they were low on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One highlight was NGC 1532, an edge on galaxy.  It was hurt a bit by the low elevation I was observing it at (about 22 degrees).  It was large in my 8mm Ethos eyepiece with a bight core a large elongated halo.  Clearly an edge on galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also re-discovered NGC 1535, a planetary nebula I'd observed before as part of another observing list dedicated to planetary nebulae.  Unfiltered, the 5mm XW eyepiece revealed the central star, a round nebula with hints of a multiple shell structure visible.  The shell structure was not visible as full shells, but more of arc segments around the core.  In looking up the object this morning, I note that it is sometimes referred to as "Cleopatra's Eye" and that Phil Harrington &lt;a href="https://www.cloudynights.com/articles/cat/column/phil-harrington-s/cosmic-challenge-ngc-1535-r3218"&gt;recently featured it&lt;/a&gt; in another of his Cosmic Challenge series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The night was somewhat memorable because it alternated in character.  There was no wind, so at first the night was totally silent and quite peaceful.  I spent some time just enjoying the naked eye sky.  The haze in the air made the brightness contrast between the local horizon and the distant shape of Maunakea quite noticeable.  Maunakea was silhouetted against the nighttime sky, but it was brighter than the nearby horizon defined by the lava rocks of Mauna Loa.  This is presumably due, at least in part, to scattered light from human activities in the saddle area: cars on the highway and lights at Pohakuloa Training Area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military at Pohakuloa Training Area made itself known in other ways though.  They were apparently doing live fire night exercises and my observing was occasionally interrupted by flares sent up to illuminate the area.  They were low on my horizon, but if you were looking at them when they lit up, it would reset your night vision adaptation.  In addition, there were occasional bursts of heavy machine gun fire and the flashes and booms of distant exposions.  At one point, I tried counting the seconds between the flash and the sound as one does with lightning.  I figured that the explosions were about 5-6 miles away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military activities, while dramatic, did not take away from a lovely night.  Having not planned on a long observing session, I started packing around 9:30PM after a quick look at the Orion Nebula.  Conditions were still good: six stars were visible in the trapezium even at the moderate magnification of my 13mm Ethos eyepiece.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="AZ100"></category></entry><entry><title>February New Moon</title><link href="/feb-2021-new-moon.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-13T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-02-13T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-02-13:/feb-2021-new-moon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A window of one night between my night support schedule for work and some poor weather in the forecast led to an observing session on the slopes of Mauna Loa on Friday night.  I got to the site well before sunset and just appreciated the slow fading of the light …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A window of one night between my night support schedule for work and some poor weather in the forecast led to an observing session on the slopes of Mauna Loa on Friday night.  I got to the site well before sunset and just appreciated the slow fading of the light on Maunakea.  The banner photo for this article was taken after the sun set for me behind the slope of Mauna Loa, but while it was still illuminating Maunakea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After dark, I spent quite a bit of time just appreciating the beautiful naked eye sky.  The clouds were well below me in the saddle and Maunakea was silhouetted against the skyglow.  Cars heading up and down the mountain traced a moving line of lights for the first part of the night and eventually quieted down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then got down to some observing with my SVX152 refractor.  I went through an observing list from the February 2019 issue of Astronomy Magazine on "Observing Stellar Blowouts".  It contained a handful of lesser known planetary nebulae.  One seemed oddly low on the horizon until I remembered that this list was probably written for mid-northern latitudes and this object (NGC 7354 in Cepheus) would be circumpolar for many of Astronomy Magazine's readers.  I caught it very low, less than 10 degrees above the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few of these nebulae stood out as really nice.  Here are slightly expanded versions of my notes taken during the night:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NGC 2371&lt;/strong&gt;: A nice little double lobed planetary nebula in my Pentax 7XW eyepiece. Better without the UHC filter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IC 418&lt;/strong&gt;: Nice, bright, blue round planetary nebula in the 7XW. Central star is easily visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NGC 2438&lt;/strong&gt;: A classic!  Beautiful in the 7XW with the UHC filter.  Round with dark center.  The filter enhances the contrast of dark central region of the nebula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent most of the rest of the night casually cruising through well known objects rising in the East, but I did bag one novelty: a naked eye asteroid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While glancing at my star chart on my iPad (I use the Sky Safari app to plan my stargazing sessions and take notes), I saw that Vesta was magnitude 6.6 in Leo.  I had truly dark skies with no haze, so I figured mag 6.6 should be within reach.  After some study of the star patterns in Leo above Denebola and some time spent concentrating on the sky and sure enough, I could trace a line of stars on the chart right to a faintly visible "star" at the position of Vesta!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="AZ100"></category></entry><entry><title>January New Moon</title><link href="/jan-2021-new-moon.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-10T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-01-10T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-01-10:/jan-2021-new-moon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got out for two observing sessions over the last few days.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday evening, I took advantage of the early darkness of winter to get a short session in and still get home for a reasonable night's sleep.  I set up at a pullout off the Mauna Loa …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got out for two observing sessions over the last few days.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday evening, I took advantage of the early darkness of winter to get a short session in and still get home for a reasonable night's sleep.  I set up at a pullout off the Mauna Loa Access Road at about 7,350 ft. elevation with my SVX152 on the AZ-100 mount.  I spent the evening working through lists of deep sky objects in Taurus and Orion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Taurus most of the initial objects on the list were part of the nebulosity surrounding the Pleaides.  All of which I'd seen before of course, but never bothered to identify by the individual catalog designations.  One surprise from the Taurus list was the planetary nebula NGC 1514.  It's a large planetary, so big that it was easily visible in the low power of a 21mm Ethos eyepiece (57x magnification, 1.75 degree FoV).  The central star was apparent and a UHC filter slightly improved the contrast.  Though there was little detail in the nebula at higher power with an 8mm Ethos eyepiece (150x magnification, 0.66 degree FoV).  Later, a search for Struve's Lost Nebula and Hind's Variable Nebula around T Tauri yielded no detection of either nebula.  I later moved on to Orion hitting all the well known objects there and cruising through some lesser known ones as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Saturday&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Thursday night was quiet and simple, Saturday night was dramatic.  The forecast was good, but driving up the Mauna Loa Access Road, I was in clouds and fog all the way to the parking lot at the end of the paved road at 11,000 feet.  There were clouds there, but I could see that they did not go much higher and I could see clear skies above them.  Since clouds tend to drop at sunset, I waited.  After sunset, the clouds were promising, but not yet clear enough to pull out the telescope and start observing.  Furthermore, there were flashes of lightning in some high clouds to the North on the other side of Maunakea.  I pulled up satellite images on my phone and could see a cell of clouds peeling off of a weather system that was passing to the northeast.  The cell split off and moved southwest through the channel between the Big Island and Maui.  That's what was generating the lightning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By this time, I'd been joined by two fellow observers and the low clouds dropped as expected, so we set up and the lightning stayed off to the North and West.  This backdrop of constant flashed of lightning and the occasional faint roll of thunder made for a dramatic night of observing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conditions were otherwise excellent, the clouds stayed low on the northern horizon and the winds were very light (&amp;lt;5 MPH).  It was, however, quite cold.  Observing at this higher elevation means the temperature was 32 F (0 C) and the humidity never really dropped.  When combined with a light breeze, this really drew the heat out of you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent the evening starting to march through a list of DSOs in Eridanus. This is an extensive list due to Eridanus's large size, so I did not finish tonight.  I was also distracted by the light show to the North and West, I spent quite a bit of time naked eye observing the sky and watching the lightning which would occasionally be bright enough to damage dark adaption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lightning show was reminiscent of the time about 6 or 7 years ago when I'd given an evening talk outdoors at the Stellarvue Dark Sky Star Party in California and had a distant summer lightning storm as a backdrop for my talk as it got dark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really regret not bringing my camera and tripod this night.  The naked eye view of the Andromeda Galaxy setting in to a bank of clouds lit up from inside by lightning was amazing and a time lapse of that would have been stunning.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="AZ100"></category></entry><entry><title>January Last Quarter</title><link href="/jan-2021-last-quarter.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-04T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-01-04T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-01-04:/jan-2021-last-quarter.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming out of the full moon time and before I started a run of support nights for work, there was a window for observing: a night where the moon would not rise until about 10:40 PM local time.  The forecast was clear of high clouds, but it had been …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming out of the full moon time and before I started a run of support nights for work, there was a window for observing: a night where the moon would not rise until about 10:40 PM local time.  The forecast was clear of high clouds, but it had been very windy recently.  Looking at the detailed wind forecast allowed for some optimism as the saddle area might be protected given the prevailing wind direction, so I packed the car and headed out.  It turns out going was a good choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stopped at a pullout along the Mauna Loa Access Road which was lower down than I usually choose.  Before sunset, the clouds were low and the pullout had a low ridge to the East.  Since I had was concerns about wind from that direction I decided to try this site despite it being about 500 feet lower elevation than my usual sites.  Observing lower down is always risky since the inversion layer can rise and cover the site with clouds, but I thought it would be worth the risk to avoid winds which were more likely higher and further to the East on the mountain.  Around sunset the inversion layer clouds crept up and almost reached the site, but they dropped and never actually covered us.  Winds were light, so it was a nice night for observing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With only about 3 hours of full darkness between the end of astronomical twilight and the arrival of moon glow, this would be a short session.  I'd prepared a few more of my constellation lists which contain deep sky objects (galaxies, globular clusters, bright nebulae, planetary nebulae, and quasars) brighter than magnitude 12 in a particular constellation.  I've found these observing lists to be a lot of fun as the magnitude limit keep things well within reach of my 152mm refractor and I sometimes come across new gems which I'm not familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tonight, I decided to hit a constellation with particular significance to me: Perseus.  My PhD dissertation focussed on outflow activity in the Perseus Molecular Cloud, so I would be seeing a few familiar objects along the way.  I'd checked out a few of these &lt;a href="dec-2020-new-moon.html"&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt;, but I wanted to finish out the constellation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the early challenges was the Perseus Galaxy Cluster.  This contains two objects on my list (the rest are fainter than magnitude 12).  The brightest member (NGC 1275 or Perseus A) was relatively easy.  The second brightest member (NGC 1272) was surprisingly difficult to spot.  I think this is because while the integrated magnitude is bright, the galaxy is large, so the surface brightness is low.  I did eventually spot it, but it took some time.  I thought this would be all I could see in the galaxy cluster since the other galaxies are fainter, but while looking for 1272, I found several other members of the cluster: NGC 1273 (mag 13.1), 1277 (mag 13.4), &amp;amp; 1278 (mag 12.4).  These were fainter, but more compact making them easier to see despite their faintness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking a break from chasing faint galaxies, I chatted a bit with Mike Connelley who was observing nearby.  While chatting I was just doing some naked eye stargazing and I realized that I had never tried to see M33 (the Triangulum Galaxy) with the naked eye.  I'd heard observers claim to detect it under dark skies and this would be a good opportunity.  I couldn't remember the exact position, but I thought I could see a faint fuzz at about the right spot.  Sure enough, when I later compared that position with a chart, it was in exactly the spot I'd thought it was.  This is the furthest object I've seen with the naked eye.  At about 2.7 million light years, it is just a bit further away than the Andromeda Galaxy (M 31).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Returning to the eyepiece, I then moved West to East through the Perseus Molucular Cloud, starting with NGC 1333 (which I mentioned last month).  I cruised through the dark clouds of Barnard 1, Barnard 4, and Barnard 5 and finished with the cluster and nebulosity IC 348.  This was the region of sky which I'd spent a lot of time observing while writing my PhD dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished out Perseus with a few more galaxies and a couple of very small planetary nebulae.  I then moved on to visit a few old friends in Orion (primarily M42), but I also stopped by the Horsehead Nebula again.  With Orion much higher in the sky than last month, the Hosehead was much easier to spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick look at the rapidly receding Mars as the moon rose concluded the night.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="AZ100"></category></entry><entry><title>December New Moon</title><link href="/dec-2020-new-moon.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-13T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-12-13T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-12-13:/dec-2020-new-moon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got out for two short observing sessions this new moon period.  The first was Friday night, it was a short session, just a couple of hours of dark time, but conditions were great.  I went to one of the pullouts off of the Mauna Loa Access Road and there …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got out for two short observing sessions this new moon period.  The first was Friday night, it was a short session, just a couple of hours of dark time, but conditions were great.  I went to one of the pullouts off of the Mauna Loa Access Road and there was no wind and the clouds were well below the saddle level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The telescope ready for a night of observing." src="images/IMG_5111.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The telescope ready for a night of observing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Friday Night&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seeing wasn't great, so I stuck to deep sky objects for observing.  I worked through an observing list of DSOs in Sculptor.  This is a constellation I'd overlooked when observing from more northern latitudes since it does not rise very high from there, but Sculptor has several nice deep sky objects within its borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highlights for me included NGC 253, the famous "Sculptor Galaxy" an edge on galaxy with what looks like texture due to myriad dust lanes.  I'd imaged NGC 253 back in 2007 shortly after I'd moved to the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="An LRGB image of NGC253, the Sculptor Galaxy" src="images/NGC253_LRGB.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An image of NGC 253 which I took in 2007 from the Visitor Information Station on Maunakea.  This was imaged using an SBIG ST-2000XM CCD with LRGB filters on a Stellarvue SV102ABV refractor with a total exposure time of 2.75 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nearby NGC 288 globular cluster is another lovely object which yielded lots of resolution in my 13mm eyepiece in the SVX152 refractor.  NGC 300, a large face on galaxy with hints of spiral arms, and NGC 55, a large edge on galaxy were nice finds as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished the night just after 9pm (about 2 hours after the end of astronomical twilight), by visiting some old friends in Perseus: NGC 1333, Barnard 1, and IC 348 which are part of the Perseus Molecular Cloud complex which was the region I studied for my PhD dissertation.  None are dramatic in the eyepiece: NGC 1333 is a reflection nebula which appears as a faint haze around a star, Barnard 1 is a dark nebula which shows up as a field devoid of bright stars, and IC 348 is a small dense open cluster next to the bright star Atik.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, a friend of mine, &lt;a href="http://www.starscapeimaging.com/index.html"&gt;Jon Talbot&lt;/a&gt; had posted an image he took of the region around NGC 1333 which reminded me that I had imaging data from the Mayall 4 meter telescope on Kitt Peak.  I sent it to him and he processed it in to a gorgeous &lt;a href="http://www.starscapeimaging.com/NGC1333%20KPNO/NGC1333_KPNO.html"&gt;color image&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Saturday Night&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, I went for another observing session.  The weather was less cooperative this time.  The clouds were higher and were alternately covering and clearing at the pullout I used the night before, so I was forced to head up the road a little higher.  Unfortunately, the wind was also an issue higher up the mountain.  It varied a bit, but was a steady 10-12 mph most of the night with gusts in the 15-18 mph range.  It seemed to pick up a bit as the night went on as well.  This severely limited high power observing and at times made even moderate magnifications difficult due to wind shake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My list of this night was DSOs in Cepheus.  Being in the galactic plane, many of these were diffuse nebulae.  While generating observing lists for the SVX152, I put a magnitude cap on objects of 12.  This is well within in the range of the scope, but it varies depending on the morphology of the object.  A small 12th magnitude galaxy or planetary nebula has all of its light packed in to a small area, so it is comparatively easy to pick out.  The huge emission nebulae in Cepheus were a challenge to pick out visually because their light is spread thinly over such a large area.  Most of the large diffuse nebulae in my notes were identifiable due to the dark areas they are embedded in, with a few having visible nebulosity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One nice find in Cepheus was NGC 40, a compact planetary nebula with a bright central star.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I've mentioned before, I've not found nebular filters all that useful from truly dark sites.  Most of the objects in this list supported that conclusion.  A few, like the Cave Nebula, did get enhanced slightly with a UHC, but were not dramatic improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I took a look at a few large nebulae around the sky to revisit this.  One early stop was the Veil Nebula in Cygnus as it was setting.  This object is notorious for being helped by an OIII filter.  Sure enough, the OIII filter significantly improved the view.  Though the nebula was very low on the horizon, so the excess sky glow down there probably made the improvement with the filter more that it would have been if it were higher up.  The North American Nebula (also in Cygnus) was similarly improved by a UHC filter, but somewhat less dramatically so.  I also checked out the Flaming Star Nebula in Auriga (which was rising), the UHC helped a bit there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other very diffuse object I tried was the Horsehead Nebula in Orion.  The nearby Flame Nebula was easy to make out and I could easily see the dark lanes which help give it the characteristic flame shape.  The Flame Nebula was not improved by a filter, in fact the unfiltered view was significantly better.  Moving on to the Horsehead, I was just able to make out the bright nebula as an area of slightly increased background.  Using nearby stars as a guide and concentrating, I was able to see a dark notch in the bright nebula at the right place and was able to get hints of the shape.  Again, the unfiltered view was a bit better to my eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Saturday observing session, a friend of mine, Olivier Guyon, was set up nearby observing with his 14 inch Celestron and showing a few of his colleagues objects in the telescope.  At one point, I overheard him talking about Andromeda and giving a tour of its numerous satellite galaxies.  This reminded me that I'd been meaning to try to see G1, the brightest globular in the Andromeda Galaxy.  I pulled it up on SkySafari.  At magnitude 13.7, it was significantly fainter than what I'd been going after in recent nights, but since it would be a compact object, it should be doable in the SVX152.  With a little work matching star patterns to verify the field, I was able to pick it out as a faint "star".  Unfortunately, there was too much wind shake to tell if it was point-like or if appeared non-stellar.  That was a highlight for me, I'd never seen a globular cluster in a different galaxy before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weather forecast for Saturday has been marginal, predicting a chance of fog for the summits.  That was one reason I'd made sure to head out on Friday, so I would get at least one night in.  Fortunately, Saturday's weather was good enough for us to observe.  While the summits were clear, I could see a layer of fog and cloud clinging to both Maunakea and Mauna Loa at high elevations.  Shortly after 10pm, those clouds swung over us and blocked our view.  The wind had also increased, so that concluded the observing session and we packed up and left.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="AZ100"></category></entry><entry><title>November New Moon</title><link href="/nov-2020-new-moon.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-15T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-11-15T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-11-15:/nov-2020-new-moon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Despite an iffy forecast for the summits, I tried to get one more night of observing in.  This time, I had arranged to meet a work colleague at the Kaohe site.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kaohe is lower down than I typically would choose due to clouds, but it has one big advantage: wind …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Despite an iffy forecast for the summits, I tried to get one more night of observing in.  This time, I had arranged to meet a work colleague at the Kaohe site.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kaohe is lower down than I typically would choose due to clouds, but it has one big advantage: wind protection.  It is behind Maunakea as far as our typical trade wind pattern is concerned and it has a line of trees which provide protection from what wind does get through.  With the wind being a potential problem, that was where we went.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At sunset, the skies directly above were clear, but there were towering clouds all around.  It looked like the clouds were receding, not building, so I set up and was eventually rewarded with completely clear skies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The night ended up being a small star party.  A total of 3 couples plus myself were there, spaced out given the everpresent coronavirus threat.  It was nice observing with people, but it was also very strange to not share views as one normally would at a star party.  I look forward to a time when that will be normal again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conditions were ok.  It was humid early in the night, presumably we were not above the inversion layer.  I think there was also a significant boundary layer not far above us because the seeing was absolutely dreadful.  Looking at planets was like trying to see things at the bottom of a moving stream.  It did improve later on though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started the night looking at planets in twilight, and that's how I discovered the terrible seeing.  I moved on to a few bright DSOs (M13, M57, M27) and took a quick look at Neptune which appeared as a slightly bluish star given the seeing conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I'd viewed Jupiter, Saturn, and Neptune at this point (with Mars a prominent target for later), I thought I'd hit the other bright planet out tonight: Uranus.  I had fun picking in out with the naked eye first before turning the telescope on it to see a small blue disk, though quite blurry with the early evening seeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By that time, it was fully dark, so I started working on my main target list for the night which was simply every galaxy, planetary nebula, globular cluster, bright nebula, and quasar brighter than 12th magnitude in Cetus.  This was an easy list to autogenerate in Sky Safari and I'd never explored Cetus much, so I thought it would be a good project.  Over the course of the night I managed to collect all 40 objects in this list.  A few of the Cetus galaxies were very challenging due not to their faintness, but to the large size (and thus low surface brightness).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were also a few gems of course.  M77 is a nice face on galaxy which I'd observed before, but some less well known objects were also fun to (re)discover.  This included NGC 246 (the "Skull Nebula") a lare planetary nebula which revealed patchy detail in the interior with my 152mm Stellarvue refractor and also NGC 908, a large edge on galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I interrupted the parade of small faint galaxies in Cetus to observe Mars as it transited.  By this time, the seeing had improved.  The clouds had long disappeared and the catabatic winds were starting to roll down the mountain and rustle the line of trees just upslope of the observing site.  This usually signals better seeing conditions at Kaohe and that was true again tonight.  Plenty of dark markings were visible on the surface along with the polar cap and some limb haze.  The details weren't as good as I'd seen in some of my previous Mars observing sessions, but they were still quite satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finishing out my Cetus list, I packed up.  The winds had increased and I was the only one left by this time.  All in all it was a gorgeous night with good darkness (SQM of 21.6) and beautiful views of Hualalai and Mauna Loa silhouetted against the night sky.  Toward the end we could see some clouds building behind Hualalai which developed in to a lightning storm.  We could see occasional bright flashes outlining the Western slope of the mountain.  It was a dramatic finish to the night.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Kaohe"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="AZ100"></category></entry><entry><title>Algol at Minimum</title><link href="/nov-2020-algol.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-09T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-11-09T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-11-09:/nov-2020-algol.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've notched a much delayed observing first tonight: I've seen Algol at minimum brightness.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with it, Algol (sometimes called the "Demon Star") is an eclipsing binary in which a pair of stars orbit around one another.  Their orbit is aligned such that the stars pass in front …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've notched a much delayed observing first tonight: I've seen Algol at minimum brightness.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with it, Algol (sometimes called the "Demon Star") is an eclipsing binary in which a pair of stars orbit around one another.  Their orbit is aligned such that the stars pass in front of one another when viewed from Earth.  When the fainter star passes in front of the brighter star, Algol appears to dim in our sky.  The dimming lasts a few hours and happens every 2.86739 days.  The dimming is visible to the naked eye and was likely known in antiquity.  The larger star is around 3 times the mass of our sun (see &lt;a href="https://www.aavso.org/vsots_betaper"&gt;the AAVSO page on Algol&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's embarrassing that I've been an avid sky watcher for this long and have never bothered to monitor Algol during an eclipse.  It was primarily a matter of planning as the dimming of Algol is only dramatic for a few hours every few days, so one has to be on the lookout for it and to have Algol up in the sky at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months ago I wrote a &lt;a href="https://github.com/joshwalawender/DarkMoonCalendar"&gt;simple script&lt;/a&gt; to put the minima of Algol on my calendar.  I've had a script I've used for a few years which puts dark moon evenings on my calendar so I don't miss even brief observing opportunities.  I simply added a step which looks for a minima of Algol happening in the evening (within 6 hours after sunset) and which happens while Algol is at least 30 degrees above the horizon.  Tonight fit the bill perfectly.  The minima was at 9:27 PM local time and twilight ended around 7:00 PM.  This meant that I could go out as soon as it was fully dark and see the star near full brightness, then go out a few hours later and see the constellation changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SkySafari map showing Algol, Almach, and Mirach." src="images/AlgolChart.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SkySafari map showing Algol, Almach, and Mirach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the first trip outside shortly after 7, Algol was bright.  Similar in brightness to Almach and Mirach above it (both are magnitude 2.1, the same as Algol is normally) and significantly brighter than Rho Persei (mag 3.4) immediately to its right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At about 9:30 PM, another look showed that Algol was much dimmer than Almach and Mirach and was similar in brightness to Rho Persei.  This does dramatically alter the constellation of Perseus.  Algol is the second brightest star in the constellation, so dimming it to roughly one third of it's normal brightness removes one of the cornerstones of the shape I'm used to seeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the movie trivia folks out there, the name Algol (derived from from Arabic &lt;em&gt;ra's al-ghul&lt;/em&gt;, see &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algol"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;) will be familiar to fans of Christopher Nolan's Dark Knight trilogy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Algol"></category><category term="Backyard Observing"></category></entry><entry><title>Mars Recedes</title><link href="/nov-2020-mars.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-07T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-11-07T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-11-07:/nov-2020-mars.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A narrow window of opportunity to observe between some bad weather forecasts and a series of nights where I had to work meant that Saturday night was the observing night for me this week.  The Moon wouldn't rise until almost midnight, so it was a good time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went up …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A narrow window of opportunity to observe between some bad weather forecasts and a series of nights where I had to work meant that Saturday night was the observing night for me this week.  The Moon wouldn't rise until almost midnight, so it was a good time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went up the Mauna Loa road despite the web cams showing the clouds up at the 11,000 foot elevation.  When I arrived at the end of the road I was still in the clouds and rain though it looked like the clouds did not go much higher.  I decided to wait it out.  It eventually did clear, but not until about about 8:45 PM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hadn't done too much planning of what to observe for this session, so I simply picked an observing list in Sky Safari at random.  This particular one I had pulled from an article in the November 2019 issue of Sky and Telescope Magazine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out the list was intended for a larger telescope than the 6 inch I'd brought.  While the first few objects (the NGC 7063 open cluster, a 10th magnitude double star, and the NGC 7013 galaxy) were easy, the next object was an 11.8 magnitude planetary.  This would normally not be too difficult, but the planetary was merged with a similar brightness background star which made it challenging to pull out.  The final two objects in the list were mag 13.4 and 14.0 planetary nebulae which I did not attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there I bounced around a bit, jumping across the sky to Almach, the gorgeous double star.  The seeing was improving and I was curious to try to resolve the BC components.  Almach's AB pair is a glorious sight: a bright color contrast double about 10" separation.  The fainter, blue companion is itself a double star of about 0.2-0.5" separation (sources differ).  Looking at the B component with the 3mm setting on the 2-4mm Nagler Zoom eyepiece (400x magnification).  I could detect elongation in moments of good seeing.  My eyeball estimate of the position angle was off by about 25 degrees from the nominal value, so it was not a clear detection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After stopping at the edge on galaxy near Almach (NGC 891), I went for Mars and spent quite some time with it.  As I've mentioned in the previous &lt;a href="sep-2020-mars.html"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="oct-2020-mars.html"&gt;entries&lt;/a&gt; here, I really don't know my Mars features all that well.  I did spend some time with SkySafari and clear identification of Valles Marinaris which was facing Earth prominently at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also played with colored filters.  I'd bought several of them years ago, but rarely used them due to the hassle of installing and removing them on an eyepiece.  Earlier this year, I picked up a Theia Filter Changer made by nPAE.  It slots in nicely in front of my diagonal on the refractor and makes it easy to change filters.  I tried a #81A (a subtle filter which enhances red) and a #41 filter (a deep red).  I initially did not think the #81A did much, but on a longer inspection, it did help with some of the dark markings on Mars.  The deep red #41 filter was such a dramatic color shift that I found it distracting.  It did help enhance dark features, but it was not a pleasing view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a long inspection of Mars, I spent a little time hitting well known objects in and around Orion (M42, M78, Flame Nebula, and NGC 1999) which were rising.  At this point the Moon was only a few degrees below the horizon, so I packed up a headed home.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Mars"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="G-11"></category></entry><entry><title>Mars Arrives</title><link href="/oct-2020-mars.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-05T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-10-05T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-10-05:/oct-2020-mars.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mars is now making its closest approach to Earth.  It turns out that this opposition of Mars will be the closest for a while due to the two planets' elliptical orbits, so this will be as big as Mars gets (as seen from Earth) for quite some time.  We won't …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mars is now making its closest approach to Earth.  It turns out that this opposition of Mars will be the closest for a while due to the two planets' elliptical orbits, so this will be as big as Mars gets (as seen from Earth) for quite some time.  We won't have a viewing opportunity as good as this again until the 2030s!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I definitely wanted to take advantage of closest approach, but I had work on Tuesday night which would keep me from observing, so I headed out for a Mars focussed observing session on the night of Oct 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried my usual strategy of driving up the Mauna Loa access road and looking for a spot above the clouds.  I started by going higher on the road, but I discovered that the winds were strong enough to be a problem for high power viewing, so I headed back to one of my favorite pullouts lower down.  This spot is sometimes a bit more protected from wind, so I set up there at sunset.  This was almost a big mistake because as I was setting up, the clouds, which had been well away down toward the Hilo side, rolled up the saddle area and covered me.  I waited them out though and they did back off around the time it became fully dark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was only an hour and a bit of dark time before the moon rose, so I only caught a few deep sky objects.  I hit a list of double stars and other objects in Cassiopeia staring with Archid (eta Cassiopeiae).  This is a nice double star, but what makes it interesting is the color contrast.  The fainter companion is redder then the primary, but our human color perception can sometimes perceive unusual colors when it doesn't have a good reference point and this can happen with stars.  To me, the companion looks slightly purple or violet which is an unusual sight.  I stopped off at a few other double stars in the area (Sigma, Rho, and Iota Cassiopeiae) and the open cluster NGC 7789 (also known as Caroline's Rose after Caroline Herschel).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to spend much of the night on a solar system tour.  I began by tracking down the asteroid Ceres, a medium bright "star" I found by star hopping to the right area of sky according to SkySafari.  Then I did a grand tour of the outer solar system checking out Neptune, Jupiter, Saturn, and Uranus.  The seeing was decent, but there was enough of a breeze to shake the view.  This meant that one had to wait patiently for a moment of stillness to get any good detail on the planets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By about 9 PM local time, Mars was high enough to get a good look.  Even impacted by the wind shake, it was glorious.  I was able to identify a few surface features from the maps in SkySafari, but the feature names in SkySafari are so dense that it is sometimes hard to figure out what you're looking at. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SkySafari map of Mars surface features." src="images/SkySafari_Mars_Surface.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SkySafari map of Mars surface features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in my last post, I'm not very good with mapping what I'm seeing to actual place names on Mars.  I'm pretty sure I could pick out Schiaparelli crater as a pale divot in the edge of the darker mare next to it and see the broad smooth dark area of Acidalia Planetia.  Later that night, as it came around in to view, I could briefly see a dark streak at the position of Valles Marineris.  The views were absolutely lovely in the moments when the wind allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the eyepiece viewing, I spent quite a while obtaining some color video for planetary imaging.  I bought a small color camera (a QHY5-III 178C) a couple months ago in anticipation of Mars opposition.  Unfortunately, I haven't had the time to play with it and get competent using it.  I have a lot to learn about planetary imaging, but at least it was fun to see the details pop out on screen as well as in the eyepiece.  A very poor processing is below using just one 5 minute sequence of images.  I'll eventually try processing some of the other sequences I took to see if I can do better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mars" src="images/Mars_20201006at2243UT.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mars at 2243 UT (on Oct 6).  Image taken using an SVX152 refractor with 2x barlow and QHY5-III 178C camera.  The best 20% of approximately 3000 frames were stacked using the SiriL software package to generate this image.  The resulting image had color balancing and an unsharp mask applied in Photoshop.  Note that this image is rotated by ~30 degrees relative to the SkySafari map above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Mars"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="G-11"></category></entry><entry><title>Mars Approaches</title><link href="/sep-2020-mars.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-13T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-09-13T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-09-13:/sep-2020-mars.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got out for a night of observing on Saturday.  I had to wedge it in between two runs of night support for my "day" job, so it was my only chance this month to get out for some observing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was quite a bit of cirrus at sunset, but …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got out for a night of observing on Saturday.  I had to wedge it in between two runs of night support for my "day" job, so it was my only chance this month to get out for some observing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was quite a bit of cirrus at sunset, but it made for some dramatic color in the clouds as can be seen in the banner photo above and in this image (taken a few minutes earlier) of Maunakea with a wisp of cirrus catching the sun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Maunakea at sunset." src="images/IMG_4799.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maunakea at sunset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up at the Wind Sock area off the Mauna Loa access road.  I did not set up immediately due to the cirrus, but the thickest parts did move off eventually.  There was still a thin covering, so it was not a night for hunting faint deep sky objects.  Fortunately, the seeing was good and there were planets available, so I spent all my time on those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was actually quite limited in what I could observe thanks to a mistake I made when packing the car.  I've recently been using my new AZ-100 alt-az mount, but since I knew that I wanted to look at planets tonight (especially Mars), I'd packed my trusty Losmandy G-11, so I'd have tracking.  Unfortunately, I'd grabbed a single 11 lb. counter wight, but my SVX152 refractor requires a 21 lb. counter weight (or two 11 lb. weights).  With insufficient counter weights, I'd be in danger of my scope flipping over and crashing in to the tripod!  I poked around in the car for a solution and eventually discovered that a Nalgene bottle full of water can hang semi-securely off the end of the counterweight shaft.  This was still a bit light, but with the clutches tightened the scope would stay where it was pointed.  Slewing from target to target was difficult.  It required one hand to move the scope, one hand to hold the Nalgene bottle so it wouldn't fall off, and was quite awkward.  Thanks to this, I observed only three objects this night: Jupiter, Saturn, and Mars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only looking at three objects was not a problem however because the seeing was excellent.  Jupiter and Saturn were gorgeous, but I was really out tonight to look at Mars which is nearing closest approach to Earth on Oct 6 (opposition is on Oct 13).  As Mars rose, I could see the polar ice cap as a very small white dot surrounded by a broader white haze.  While I absolutely love looking at Mars, I'm embarrassed to say that I don't know the names of the features very well at all.  With good viewing opportunities only coming every 2+ years, I never commit them to memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the polar cap and haze, there was a limb haze on one side of the planet and a bit of pale haze surrounding the other polar ice cap (which was tilted away from Earth and thus not visible).  There were a trio of beautiful dark markings, almost comet-like parallel streaks on the planet.  Looking at the Mars map in Sky Safari, I think these were Terra Cimmeria, Tyrrhena Terra, and Promethei Terra, but there's a confusion of detail and labels in that map, so I may be getting those wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seeing was excellent as I mentioned.  There was little or no bulk image motion, but as you watched additional fine details would occasionally snap in to view.  It felt almost like a contrast effect rather than a sharpness effect, but each of these dark areas would occasionally grow very detailed around the edges and the shapes would take on an incredible richness of detail.  I spent quite a bit of time using the 2.5mm setting on my 2-4mm Nagler Zoom eyepiece (which is 480 magnification).  I'd originally thought I'd probably sell this eyepiece when I got the 152 because the magnifications would be too high, but it has turned out useful to have that range and the ability to tune the magnification to the seeing conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, despite cirrus and only partially functional equipment, it was a very satisfying night.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Mars"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="G-11"></category></entry><entry><title>Two Nights of Perseid Viewing</title><link href="/aug-2020-perseids.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-17T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-08-17T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-08-17:/aug-2020-perseids.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got out for two observing sessions around the peak of the Perseid Meteor Shower.  The first, a relatively short session on Wednesday, the second was a longer session on Saturday night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday Night&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, I was up on Mauna Loa to do some work on a project hosted …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got out for two observing sessions around the peak of the Perseid Meteor Shower.  The first, a relatively short session on Wednesday, the second was a longer session on Saturday night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday Night&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, I was up on Mauna Loa to do some work on a project hosted at the NOAA Mauna Loa Observatory and I finished up shortly after sunset before it was fully dark.  The clouds were right at the level of the observatory so I was in and out of them while I was finishing up.  I hopped in the car, drove down the road, and emerged from the clouds (which were dissipating anyway) after a few miles.  I pulled over and set up at the "Wind Sock" pullout along the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set up a camera to try to catch some Perseid meteors even though the peak of meteor showers typically doesn't start until after local midnight.  While I did set up the telescope for a bit of viewing, I spent most of my time just doing some naked eye stargazing and enjoying the night.  With work the next morning, I only stayed a couple of hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's prime time for one of my favorite objects in the sky: R Coronae Australis (R CrA).  It is in the south, at a declination of -37 degrees, but from Hawaii it gets high enough to enjoy.  Located below the teapot of Sagittarius, Coronae Australis is a C-shaped constellation of moderately bright stars.  The R CrA complex is a group of objects composed of NGC 6723, 6726, 6727, and 6729.  The first of these (NGC 6723) is a globular cluster, small in comparison to the great clusters, but still a nice view in my 152mm refractor.  The other three (NGC 6726, 6727, and 6729) are all reflection nebula which are part of the same star forming cloud.  The NGC 6726 and 6727 reflection nebulae are brighter, easily detectable in the eyepiece, and slightly blueish (dramatically blue in photographs).  The smaller NGC 6729 is fainter, but triangular shaped with two stars embedded in it.  One of those stars (at the apex of the triangle) is a very young protostar whose outflows have carved the cavity in the cloud which is now illuminated by the star.  This is R CrA itself and it is one of the youngest stars you can see with your eye in an eyepiece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I imaged this region back in July of 2007 and it is one of my favorite astrophotos that I've taken:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The R Coronae Australis region." src="images/RCrA.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The R Coronae Australis region.  Imaged with an SBIG ST-2000XM CCD on a Stellarvue SV102ABV refractor at f/6.4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hit a few more highlight objects of the Milky Way that night, but I also managed to catch Comet NEOWISE one more time.  It is no longer visible to the naked eye.  I tried quite hard as it should have been at the edge of detectability with an estimated magnitude of 6.5-7, but it was close to the Zodiacal Light, so that may have impacted my ability to see it.  I did of course see it in binoculars and in the telescope.  The telescopic view lacked the starlike core and big expansive tail which was visible back in July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I thoroughly enjoyed the naked eye views of the Milky Way, I did not see many Perseid meteors this night.  Perhaps the problem was splitting my time between the camera (taking a time lapse), the telescope, and naked eye viewing, but I saw only a handful of faint meteors, some of which were not Perseids (evidenced by their direction of travel not lining up with the radiant).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time lapse was marred by more flare activity at the Pohakuloa military base which brightened the sky background periodically.  While there were many satellite streaks in the time lapse, there were few meteors.  I was pointing fairly low on the horizon to get Maunakea in the image, so perhaps that impacted the meteor count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Saturday Night&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I observed again on Saturday, this time it was a trip dedicated to observing rather than a chance opportunity like Wednesday night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met up with two other astronomers at a large pullout lower down on Mauna Loa than the "Wind Sock" area from Wednesday.  As is the norm nowadays, we set up a modest, socially distant way apart from each other, but it was nice to have other observers to chat with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conditions were near perfect.  Being lower down, it was warmer and there was very little wind.  There were some clouds threatening early, both high cirrus, and low ground fog creeping up from the Hilo side of the saddle, but both dissipated as it got fully dark.  Better yet, the seeing was excellent.  The sharpness of the views of Jupiter, Saturn, and Mars were stunning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started the night going through a set of deep sky objects described in this month's &lt;em&gt;Astronomy&lt;/em&gt; magazine.  The faintest ones were a real challenge in my 152mm refractor.  I didn't quite finish the list as the exclamations from the others about the seeing on Jupiter and Saturn convinced me to cut DSO viewing short and go look at the planets.  It was worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was not perfectly set up for planetary viewing.  While my refractor performs spectacularly, I was observing on an un-motorized alt-az mount (a Rowan AZ-100).  Its slow motion controls made planetary viewing at high power feasible, but a tracking mount would have let me push the power even higher.  I maxed out at 240x using a Pentax 5XW eyepiece.  The next step would have been a 2-4mm Nagler Zoom, but the combination of higher power and smaller apparent field of view of that eyepiece would have meant that the planet was in the field only briefly before needing a tweak with the slow motion controls.  I'm considering motorizing this mount and this was another reason to push me to undertake that project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In between periodic visits to Jupiter and Saturn, I hit a few objects which benefit from good seeing.  Mostly small planetary nebulae like the Saturn Nebula and the Cat's Eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I packed up at about 1:30am.  I wanted to stay until Mars was nice and high for viewing.  Mars was lovely.  It is still my favorite planet to view and I'm looking forward to opposition.  The planet is now getting quite large, it was 16.6 arcseconds on Saturday night.  I could easily see the polar ice cap, the gibbous phase, and a plethora of dark markings on the surface.  I love the subtle detail that gets revealed by a long look at Mars in the eyepiece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd set up my camera on a tracking mount similar to Wednesday night.  This time I spent most of the time aimed at the Winter Milky Way, West of the radiant which was still rising, to try to catch some Perseids.  As before, the number of satellite trails far outstripped the meteors.  I'm not sure there's enough meteors in the sequence to make a nice composite image, but I'm going to try.  That'll take some time to process, so I'll have to try to put that together in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Comets"></category><category term="Meteor Shower"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="AZ100"></category></entry><entry><title>The Thorn in the Great Bear's Paw</title><link href="/july-2020-comet-neowise4.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-24T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-07-24T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-07-24:/july-2020-comet-neowise4.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One more observing trip up to Mauna Loa to check out Comet NEOWISE before the moon becomes too bright.  I had to drive up to the 9000 ft. level to get away from clouds and after setting up, they did roll over me briefly before settling down just after sunset …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One more observing trip up to Mauna Loa to check out Comet NEOWISE before the moon becomes too bright.  I had to drive up to the 9000 ft. level to get away from clouds and after setting up, they did roll over me briefly before settling down just after sunset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've wanted to get an image of the comet with a wide field lens showing the constellation of Ursa Major as well.  The phrase "the thorn in the great bear's paw" has been in my head since first seeing the comet, but my last few trips to the coast to get a photo illustrating it were hampered by clouds.  This time, however, I was successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Thorn in the Great Bear's Paw." src="images/6D-0290.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Thorn in the Great Bear's Paw&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crescent moon is just off the left edge of the image and is brightening the sky a bit, but I'm quite pleased with the image.  I did a little Photoshop work to enhance the color in the brighter stars and obviously to add the constellation lines.  Over the time I've been watching it the comet has moved from the forepaw of the Great Bear to the hind paw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a similar wide angle image, but of the comet and Maunakea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Comet NEOWISE and Maunakea" src="images/6D-0297.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comet NEOWISE and Maunakea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I made yet another time lapse of the comet setting next to Maunkea.  This was taken with the camera on a tracking platform, so the sky appears to stay still and the horizon rotates up to cover it.  A crescent moon is just out of the frame to the left and is what causes the lens flare visible at the beginning of the sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ske0LpjnLRw" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting aspect of this sequence is that if you look closely at the horizon where the comet is setting toward the end, you'll nee a number of streaks in the sky.  I did a bit of digging and a few are meteors, but most are satellites and many of those are the Starlink satellite constellation which has been &lt;a href="https://aas.org/press/aas-issues-position-statement-satellite-constellations"&gt;worrying astronomers&lt;/a&gt; due to the potential impact on astronomical observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time lapse was somewhat frustrating because I had to drop several frames due to car headlights.  You can see occasional stuttering in the sequence because of that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Comets"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="Photography"></category><category term="Time Lapse"></category></entry><entry><title>A Night of Solar System Viewing</title><link href="/july-2020-comet-neowise3.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-21T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-07-21T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-07-21:/july-2020-comet-neowise3.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;A Night of Solar System Viewing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, I made another trip up the the saddle area between Mauna Loa and Maunakea to look at Comet NEOWISE.  The forecast was better and sure enough the inversion layer clouds were very low.  We only had to drive up the road to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;A Night of Solar System Viewing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, I made another trip up the the saddle area between Mauna Loa and Maunakea to look at Comet NEOWISE.  The forecast was better and sure enough the inversion layer clouds were very low.  We only had to drive up the road to about 7,800 ft. elevation to be well clear of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With clear dark skies, the comet was much easier to find in twilight and made more of a visual impact with the naked eye.  The only thing marring the view was that the military base at Pohakuloa was doing some sort of night training exercises and was launching flares, presumably to illuminate the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Comet NEOWISE closeup." src="images/6D-9870.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comet NEOWISE closeup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took some photos and a time lapse on a tracking mount.  Because of this, the comet stays stationary and the horizon appears to rise to cover it.  This is actually a better representation of what is actually happening as the stars "setting" is actually due to the Earth's rotation causing our horizon to rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the time lapse below, you can see the flares illuminating the sky from just outside the field of view.  This is what causes the flashes of orange color in the sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comet also appears to change color and fade as it gets close to the horizon, this is due to our atmosphere scattering the blue light away.  It is the same phenomenon which causes sunsets to look orange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look closely at the time lapse, you can see the nucleus of the comet moving slightly against the background stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xYiP51hmqqY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this session, I'd set up my 152mm refractor.  The view of the comet in it was stunning.  While binoculars reveal the full extent of the tails (both dust and ion tails were visible), the telescope showed a round compact halo around a pinpoint, star like nucleus.  One could also see subtle shading in the tails near the nucleus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Saturn, Jupiter, and Mars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the comet set, I turned to the other showpieces of the sky right now: Jupiter and Saturn.  While I've observed from various locations on Mauna Loa before, this was a particularly good night with little wind.  The wind is often what limits good viewing there as it shakes the telescope.  This lack of wind was accompanied by truly excellent seeing which I did not expect.  The views of the planets were spectacular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jupiter had a richness of detail in the belts which I'd only seen a few times.  The four moons each had their own character and were clearly not point sources.  Ganymede and Callisto in particular were little tan disks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturn was, if anything, even more spectacular.  There was subtle shading in the planet and rings which I'd rarely seen.  The only better view of the planet I've ever had was on a trip many years ago to look through the 82 inch Struve telescope at McDonald Observatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent quite a while just drinking in the views of these two planets.  I did spend a few minutes looking at other objects which would be particularly suited to good seeing.  The Lambda Cygni double star (0.9" separation, 1.7 magnitude contrast) was "Split nicely!  Companion in airy ring of primary." and Tau Cygni (1.0" separation, 2.8 magnitude contrast) was split with more difficulty thanks to the more contrast, with the faint companion appearing as a slightly brighter spot in the airy ring of the primary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I returned to Jupiter and Saturn though to appreciate those views for a while.  I lingered so long that Mars rose and despite it being only 10 degrees or so above the horizon, I took a look.  The seeing was obviously worse down at this elevation, but the views were still pretty good.  Polar caps and dark markings on the surface were visible.  The gibbous phase of the planet made it feel more three dimensional than it does at opposition when it is fully illuminated.  I'm really looking forward to this upcoming Mars opposition when the planet will appear much larger and (hopefully) more details will be visible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Comets"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="G-11"></category><category term="Photography"></category><category term="Time Lapse"></category></entry><entry><title>Comet NEOWISE from the Coast</title><link href="/july-2020-comet-neowise2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-18T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-07-18T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-07-18:/july-2020-comet-neowise2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Comet NEOWISE from the Coast&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another attempt at seeing Comet NEOWISE (C/2020 F3) last night was hampered by high cirrus, though the clouds resulted in some spectacular color in the sky at sunset.  We'd driven down to the coast below the Kohala mountains along the Akoni Pule Highway.  Our …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Comet NEOWISE from the Coast&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another attempt at seeing Comet NEOWISE (C/2020 F3) last night was hampered by high cirrus, though the clouds resulted in some spectacular color in the sky at sunset.  We'd driven down to the coast below the Kohala mountains along the Akoni Pule Highway.  Our first site, up at the north end of the island, had too many low level clouds, so we headed south and ended up at a pullout along the road about half way between Kawaihae and Mahukona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even there, a few low level clouds coming over the Kohalas kept blocking out the comet, so while we did see it naked eye and with binoculars it was never quite as dramatic as &lt;a href="july-2020-comet-neowise.html"&gt;yesterday's view&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sunset colors" src="images/6D-9679.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunset colors in the patch of cirrus that stubbornly refused to move and partially blocked our view of the comet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Comet NEOWISE" src="images/6D-9705.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comet NEOWISE through a gap in the clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4SfII_weMh0" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A time lapse of the clouds passing in front of the comet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Comets"></category><category term="Kohala Coast"></category><category term="Photography"></category><category term="Time Lapse"></category></entry><entry><title>Comet NEOWISE in Twilight</title><link href="/july-2020-comet-neowise.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-17T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-07-17T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-07-17:/july-2020-comet-neowise.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Comet NEOWISE in Twilight&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday evening I took a drive up the Mauna Loa access road to meet some friends to look for Comet NEOWISE (C/2020 F3).  We found a few adjacent pullouts along the road and we all watched the northeastern horizon as it got dark looking …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Comet NEOWISE in Twilight&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday evening I took a drive up the Mauna Loa access road to meet some friends to look for Comet NEOWISE (C/2020 F3).  We found a few adjacent pullouts along the road and we all watched the northeastern horizon as it got dark looking for the comet.  We eventually spotted it in binoculars through a gap in some cirrus that was skirting the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it got dark, the comet and its tail became visible to the naked eye.  The tail was an arc a few degrees long and could be traced maybe 5 degrees in binoculars.  The view was somewhat limited by the cirrus, but the clouds did add some drama to photographs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Comet NEOWISE" src="images/6D-9429-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comet with the last remnants of sunset colors in the clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Comet NEOWISE" src="images/6D-9528-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comet with both tails (dust and ion) visible through the cirrus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Comet NEOWISE" src="images/6D-9537-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A wide field image of the comet setting next to Maunakea with Haleakala on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Comet NEOWISE" src="images/6D-9557-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comet setting next to Haleakala.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I combined a few sequences of images together in to time lapse videos of the comet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dIZLADFSjDs" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thin cirrus clouds streaming past the comet as the last colors of sunset disappear from the clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aiYLiK5LRps" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comet NEOWISE sets behind Haleakala (on the island of Maui) with the west slope of Maunakea in the foreground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Comets"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="Photography"></category><category term="Time Lapse"></category></entry><entry><title>A Foggy Night on Mauna Loa</title><link href="/june13-observing-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-14T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-06-14T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-06-14:/june13-observing-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;June 13&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went up on Saturday night for my second observing night of the weekend.  The inversion layer clouds could not have been more different.  The clouds last night at Kaohe were almost non-existant and Kaohe got noticeably less humid around 9pm when the down slope catabatic wind started …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;June 13&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went up on Saturday night for my second observing night of the weekend.  The inversion layer clouds could not have been more different.  The clouds last night at Kaohe were almost non-existant and Kaohe got noticeably less humid around 9pm when the down slope catabatic wind started up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tonight, the inversion was well defined, thick with clouds, and high.  From the site I chose (the "wind sock" along the Mauna Loa access road), the clouds were just below me at sunset and I could see that Kaohe was covered with a thick layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worse than that, as the sun set, the clouds crept higher and higher until we could feel droplets of water hitting us.  Though we could still see stars, the blowing mist kept the covers on the telescopes until about 9:15 PM which is when we finally emerged from the clouds.  It wasn't a big shift, the clouds were still thick just below us on the slopes of the mountain, but it was enough to observe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four of us that were there observed for a few hours.  I packed up first at about 11:15 PM.  The seeing was variable, with some good moments and then deteriorating.  The wind was a constant 10 mph which limited high power viewing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I watched Io emerge from in front of Jupiter with the planet very low on the horizon during that period of good seeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the period of fog, my iPad which I'd set out in preparation for observing got soaked and the cold and wind drained the battery, so I did not have a chance to take my usual observing notes for this session.  It recovered once it dried off and was plugged in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did manage to see comet C/2019 T2 PanSTARRS in the SVX152.  It was easily bright enough to see, but the nucleus was indistinct and elongated with no sharp core to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent most of the rest of the night hitting some nice bright targets similar to last night and with the observing going a bit later, I got to spend some time in the Summer Milky Way which was rising.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="AZ100"></category></entry><entry><title>A Quick Observing Session at Kaohe</title><link href="/june12-observing-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-13T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-06-13T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-06-13:/june12-observing-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;June 12&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got out for a short, low key observing session at the Kaohe site on Friday night.  A colleague from work who had expressed interest in coming observing met me up there and we spent the evening checking out some highlights of the spring sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was clear …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;June 12&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got out for a short, low key observing session at the Kaohe site on Friday night.  A colleague from work who had expressed interest in coming observing met me up there and we spent the evening checking out some highlights of the spring sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was clear when I arrived before sunset and the views of sunset were beautiful.  It was humid for the early part of the night and as it got dark, I could see some ground fog forming around the pu'u just uphill of the observing site.  I was worried the clouds would form just above us, but the skies stayed clear and very dark.  I took a few SQM readings later in the night and got an average of about 21.9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The SVX152 set up at Kaohe." src="images/APC_0055.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SVX152 set up at Kaohe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One interesting feature of the night was the sound of military helicopters doing training exercises in "aviation gunnery".  I'd heard the helicopters before sunset, but never saw them.  After dark, we would hear the gunfire and explosions and could see some of the tracer rounds against the backgrop of Mauna Loa.  The tracers were red and looked like lasers from a SciFi movie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We opened the observing with a few bright globulars: Omega Centauri, M5, and M13.  This was in the lingering twilight, but they were bright enough to puch through and show some detail.  We revisited Omega Centauri after it got fully dark and it was much more impressive then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it got fully dark we switched to some galaxies: M81 &amp;amp; 82, M51, M101.  M51 was particularly good with the spiral arms nicely visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that the Milky Way was low on the south and eastern horizons, we stuck with galaxies for a while.  We visited the Sombrero Galaxy which had lovely definition in the dark lane, then jumped over to the Antennae galaxies (NGC 4038 and 4039).  The antennae were small, but you could see the V-shaped pairing of the two galaxies.  While in Corvus we stopped at the lovely NGC 4361 planetary nebula as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking at galaxies at this time of year one has to visit the Virgo cluster of course.  We stopped at the lovely Needle Galaxy (NGC 4565) and got a nice view of the dark lane cutting through it before hitting Markarian's Chain (M86, M84, "The Eyes") and the galaxies around it including M87 (Virgo A).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swinging back to the north we visited a couple of planetary nebulae: the Owl (M97) and its neighboring edge on galaxy M108 plus the Cat's Eye (NGC 6543).  Then swung south to take a look at the irregularly shaped Bug Nebula (NGC 6302) and the Northern Jewelbox cluster (NGC 6231).  With a UHC filter, we could see the diffuse nebula IC 4628 just on the north edge of the loose open cluster Collinder 316. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We finished off the night in the south where the Milky Way was rising.  Most of these objects were low, but it was still fun to visit some highlights of the Summer Milky Way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hit the globulars M10, M12, and M22.  Then lingered on the beautiful Swan Nebula (M17) and Eagle Nebula (M16).  The swan was helped a bit by a UHC filter at this low elevation.  We checked out the Ink Blot dark nebula which is next to Djorg 2 which I'd always assumed was a dense open cluster, but Sky Safari has it down as a globular.  Sliding North just a bit to hit the Lagoon (M8) and Trifid (M20).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We finished the night watching a very fuzzy (due to the low elevation) Io disappear in to Jupiter’s shadow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Kaohe"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="AZ100"></category></entry><entry><title>A Trio of May Observing Sessions</title><link href="/may-observing-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-24T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-05-24T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-05-24:/may-observing-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I managed to get out for three nights of observing during this dark of the moon period all using my SVX152 on the Rowan AZ-100.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;May 15&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nice dark moon night spent at the parking lot at the end of the Mauna Loa Access Road.  Nice conditions, but occasional …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I managed to get out for three nights of observing during this dark of the moon period all using my SVX152 on the Rowan AZ-100.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;May 15&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nice dark moon night spent at the parking lot at the end of the Mauna Loa Access Road.  Nice conditions, but occasional wind shake limited high power work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I caught a pair of comets early in the evening: PANSTARRS (C/2017 T2) and ATLAS (C/2019 Y1).  Then, I continued working through the list of objects in Hydra which I'd worked on in April, finally finishing the list of 60 objects.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highlight of the night was finding SN 2020ifo in M61. This was very faint and I didn't expect to see in in "only" a 6 inch telescope, but I did tease it out by finding a star that wasn't on the sky chart and verified the position later against catalogs. Also tried to pick up some faint stars just to see how deep I could go. I visually got a lot deeper than I expected bagging a couple of mag 14.X stars and the SN was somewhere in that range as well&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;May 18&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a short solo session at a pullout below the top of the Mauna Loa Access Road.  Similar to how I'd built lists of deep sky objects (DSOs) in Hydra for previous observing sessions, this time I started on a list of DSOs in Crater and Corvus.  These are smaller constellations, so it was much shorter list (18 objects) than the list for Hydra (60 objects) and I finished it in this session.  I finished up with a few bright favorites that were rising (the Ring Nebula) and packed up before it got too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;May 23&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May 23 was a good session for me.  Some of the WHAC members were thinking of heading to the Ka'ohe site and it turns out that heading for the Mauna Loa access road was a good call as it allowed me to keep driving up far enough to get above the clouds.  I'd initially stopped at a site lower down, but even through the clouds were receding before sunset, they were still above me, so I went all the way to the end of the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SVX152 set up at the end of the Mauna Loa Access Road with Maunakea in the background." src="images/6D-7947.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SVX152 set up at the end of the Mauna Loa Access Road with Maunakea in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trio of the crescent moon, Venus, and Mercury setting in twilight was spectacular:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The crescent moon, Venus, and Mercury setting." src="images/6D-7965.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crescent moon, Venus, and Mercury setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started the night with the goal of going through an article on face on and edge on galaxies from the May issue of Astronomy magazine.  About half way through that list I got distracted and started looking at some close doubles (the seeing was variable with some very good moments).  I split a tight 0.9" double with a pair of clean airy disks in those good moments of seeing.  Fortunately the winds were very light for much of the night which limited wind shake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that brief interlude, which allowed some of my galaxy targets to move away from the zenith, I got back to my list and finished it.  It was a good exercise and kept the view of galaxy after galaxy interesting because they were all chosen to be good examples of face on or edge on galaxies.  The order of edge on and face on alternated in the list which made each a unique shape.  There were a number I was unfamiliar with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end of the night concluded with a look at a few bright interesting targets.  Antares, a nice color contrast double.  The deep orange of the bright primary makes the fainter secondary look purple or violet to my eye (though I'm sure it is blue in reality).  The Cat's Eye nebula was also a fun stop.  I tried comparing the unfiltered view with UHC and OIII filters.  In my view, the UHC did not help at all.  The OIII really punched up the contrast and did help with some features, but the unfiltered view was my favorite.  I have a new quick filter exchanger from nPAE which makes adding or removing filters easier, so I'm hoping to do more of these comparisons and use some mild color filters on planets later this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While observing, I got a nice time lapse of the center of the Milky Way rising over the slope of Mauna Loa as some night clouds passed along the southern horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iygaQDIiCzY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a very good night.  Good seeing (at times), dark (SQM 21.82), with low winds.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="AZ100"></category></entry><entry><title>A Pair of April Observing Sessions</title><link href="/april-observing-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-04-27T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-04-27T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-04-27:/april-observing-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I managed to go out on April 17 and 26th bracketing the new moon.  I spent both nights working with my Stellarvue SVX152 refractor  on a new alt-az mount (the Rowan AZ100).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve never explored some sections of the southern skies properly, so at home, I’d used Sky …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I managed to go out on April 17 and 26th bracketing the new moon.  I spent both nights working with my Stellarvue SVX152 refractor  on a new alt-az mount (the Rowan AZ100).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve never explored some sections of the southern skies properly, so at home, I’d used Sky Safari to build a list of all galaxies, globular clusters, and nebulae brighter than 12th magnitude in Hydra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the 26th, the moon was up for a few hours after sunset.  I’d planned on using the time to try to split some tight double stars, but the seeing was poor.  It was very dark once the moon went down, so the DSO hunting went well.  I logged 28 objects in each session, most of those were new for me as I typically don’t make notes for familiar objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were fun sessions as I got to know my new mount.  I ended up using digital setting circles (DSCs) to find objects in my observing lists.  I enjoyed that more than I thought I would.  I've been a purist for visual observing my entire life, forsaking the use of "go to" mounts in favor of old fashioned star hopping.  I'd recently migrated to the use of a digital finder chart (SkySafari running on an iPad) instead of old fashioned paper charts (Uranometria 2000), but I still found objects by star hopping until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This "push to" observing with the DSCs is a great middle ground between star hopping and go to.  The Rowan AZ-100 has slip clutches, so you just push the scope where you want it to go, guided by the display on the DSCs.  This means I can move between objects faster as my push to speed is usually a lot quicker than the slew speed of typical motorized mounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big advantage of DSCs which I had not appreciated until now is that I no longer have to crane my neck to look along the telescope tube for pointing.  I typically use a red dot finder of some sort for rough pointing, then go to either an optical finder scope or a wide field eyepiece in the main scope.  Using the red dot finder sometimes requires contortions with a long refractor like my 152.  Between avoiding those neck straining contortions and having a nice adjustable chair to put me at the right height for looking through the eyepiece, it was a lot less tiring to go hunting for objects.  I think I'm a convert.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="AZ100"></category></entry><entry><title>A Social Distancing Half Messier Marathon</title><link href="/messier-marathon-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-03-22T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2020-03-22T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-03-22:/messier-marathon-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I practiced some good social distancing and went out for a solo observing session on Sunday night.  I got to the site (a pullout on the Mauna Loa access road at about 8600 ft elevation) right at sunset and set up quickly.  The original plan from months ago was to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I practiced some good social distancing and went out for a solo observing session on Sunday night.  I got to the site (a pullout on the Mauna Loa access road at about 8600 ft elevation) right at sunset and set up quickly.  The original plan from months ago was to attempt a Messier Marathon around this time in March with a bunch of other people, but with the COVID-19 crisis gatherings were not recommended and with a crazy week at work leading up to this, I didn’t want to attempt an all nighter.  I figure if there can be such a thing as a “half marathon” for runners, I could try a Half Messier Marathon.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conditions were beautiful with very light winds.  At sunset I could see the clouds of the inversion layer below.  One disadvantage of the Mauna Loa Access Road area is that the clouds tend to be pushed up the northeastern slope of Mauna Loa by the prevailing winds, so as you drive up the access road going east on the north slope of the mountain, the clouds tend to rise along with you.  This meant I went a bit further up than I’d planned, hence the arrival right at sunset.  I set up the scope, an SVX152 on a Losmandy G-11 and started trying to spot the constellations setting in the West, so I could begin with my first objects of the night: the M31 group (M31, M32, M110).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found Mirach by eye and star hopped over to the area where M31 should be, still too bright.  I wanted a while and the core of M31 slowly emerged from the sunset glow.  M32 followed soon after.  M110 was a bit harder and I was beginning to wonder if I’d miss it, but it also emerged about 10 or so minutes later.  I moved on to M33 which is a bit higher in the sky, but larger and more diffuse.  Fortunately the galaxy was bright enough to punch through.  I was even able to find it without star hopping, just pointing to the right region and scanning, then verifying its position against the star patterns on my star chart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next was M74, the biggest challenge of the night.  I reasonably quickly found the position based on the star patterns in the eyepiece, but would the sky get dark enough while the galaxy was still high enough to be seen?  It took almost 20 minutes, but I did just get it.  At about 6 degrees elevation I declared victory.  I could not hold the galaxy with direct vision, but by nudging the scope a bit, I could see the faintest glow moving against the fading twilight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cetus A (M77) followed and it was easy in comparison.  It was now dark enough and the objects I was looking at were not as low in the twilight.  The Little Dumbbell (M76) and M103 followed quickly.  While I was up North in Cassiopeia, I stopped to look at Comet PanSTARRS (C/2017 T2) which I had not looked at during previous observing sessions.  It was a lopsided fuzzball affected a bit by the low elevation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, the rush of catching things in twilight was mostly over.  I hit the M34 cluster, then stopped to look at asteroid Vesta which was easily recognizable as a medium bright star which was not there in the star chart.  I then moved from south to north through the winter Milky Way, hitting objects in Lepus, Orion, Taurus, and Auriga (along with a few non-Messier objects which were on the way).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked my was through the objects in rough RA order.  When I neared the meridian, I jumped across to the east to avoid the neck strain of trying to find things near the zenith.  This was now galaxy country, well away from the winter Milky Way.  Galaxies in Leo and Ursa Major were next on the list.  Then I took a short beak before tackling the Virgo cluster, which is always a landmark in any Messier Marathon.  The Virgo cluster of galaxies is fun, but also a bit challenging as it is easy to find galaxies there, but not always easy to positively identify them, so working through in a systematic manner helps.  I started with Markarian’s Chain, catching both Messier objects and some non-Messier as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Virgo, I picked up a few objects I’d skipped earlier that were now a bit lower in the West and easier to access, then flipped back to the East to work my way down toward the horizon for all the objects over there which were not in Virgo.  I wrapped up by finding objects in the very top of Scorpius (M80 and M4) which was just rising.  M4 was just 7.5 degrees above the horizon when I got there.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a few Messier objects that were technically up at this point, but too low to reasonably observe, so I took a quick look at the Jewel Box in Crux (the Southern Cross) which was now up and declared this to be a complete Half Messier Marathon.  I’d started with objects setting in the west and worked my way eastward until there was nothing left that was at a reasonable elevation.  To continue the marathon properly, I’d have to take a few hours break to let things rise.  My first Messier entry was M31 at 7:19 PM, my last was M4 at midnight on the dot.  I observed 69 Messier objects in total (out of 110) and 98 objects were in my log in total including non-Messier objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conditions were great.  I did not really get a sense of the seeing as I spent most of my time at low to medium power (21mm = 57x, 13mm = 92x, and a bit of 8mm = 150x) and was focusing on DSOs rather than objects with lots of fine detail.  Winds were very light (an unusual occurrence on Mauna Loa) with a whisper of down slope catabatic winds.  The inversion was well behaved down below, occasionally filling in the saddle from the east up to Pohakuloa Training Area.  I could see a little vehicle activity on Maunakea across the way: a few cars going up or down, but not the large crowds that are usually visible as chains of headlights coming down the mountain.  I took a number of SQM measurements of the sky background brightness and once the Milky Way got away from the Zenith, the SQM values improved to about 21.85 on average, an excellent night.  My initial impression was that it was a bit hazy or with low transparency, but I think it was just that I was at such a nice dark site that the sky was considerably brighter than the surrounding landforms which are dark lava on Mauna Loa.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Observing Reports"></category><category term="Messier Marathon"></category><category term="Mauna Loa"></category><category term="SVX152"></category><category term="G-11"></category></entry></feed>