<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Twilight Landscapes Blog - Podcasting</title><link href="blog.twilightlandscapes.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="blog.twilightlandscapes.com/feeds/podcasting.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>blog.twilightlandscapes.com/</id><updated>2021-02-07T00:00:00-10:00</updated><entry><title>Halema'uma'u Time Lapse</title><link href="blog.twilightlandscapes.com/feb-2021-halemaumau.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-07T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-02-07T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-02-07:blog.twilightlandscapes.com/feb-2021-halemaumau.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I spent this past weekend in &lt;a href="https://www.nps.gov/havo/index.htm"&gt;Hawaii Volcanoes National Park&lt;/a&gt;.  It was my first trip there since the most recent eruption started in late December.  Hiking out to one of the overlooks situated almost due East of the crater late at night meant we had that whole section of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I spent this past weekend in &lt;a href="https://www.nps.gov/havo/index.htm"&gt;Hawaii Volcanoes National Park&lt;/a&gt;.  It was my first trip there since the most recent eruption started in late December.  Hiking out to one of the overlooks situated almost due East of the crater late at night meant we had that whole section of the park to ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is not currently a direct view to the lava lake growing within the Halema'uma'u crater, it does light up the sky in the area producing a dramatic glow above the crater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the time lapse video below, you can see the glow of the Halema'uma'u lava lake against the night sky.  The constellations of Orion and Taurus can be seen as well as the Pleiades cluster.  Mars makes a brief appearance setting below the cloud and behind the column of vog rising up from the lava lake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="700" height="394" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-FwMzIJLW0c" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="Podcasting"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Volcano"></category><category term="Photography"></category><category term="Time Lapse"></category></entry><entry><title>What’s It Like to Work In Professional Astronomy?</title><link href="blog.twilightlandscapes.com/feb-2021-space-junk.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-01T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T00:00:00-10:00</updated><author><name>Josh Walawender</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-02-01:blog.twilightlandscapes.com/feb-2021-space-junk.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week I was interviewed by Tony Darnell and Dustin Gibson of the Space Junk Podcast about what it is like to work at the big research telescopes.  The episode went live today.  It was a fun discussion which touched on a variety of topics including some of the cool …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week I was interviewed by Tony Darnell and Dustin Gibson of the Space Junk Podcast about what it is like to work at the big research telescopes.  The episode went live today.  It was a fun discussion which touched on a variety of topics including some of the cool technology I get to work with in my job, the latest research to come out of the Keck Observatory, and how people can get involved through citizen science.  Listen in your favorite podcasting app or via the embedded web player below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://anchor.fm/spacejunk/embed/episodes/Whats-It-Like-to-Work-In-Professional-Astronomy-eppbsb/a-a4gt00i" height="102px" width="400px" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="Podcasting"></category><category term="Astronomy"></category><category term="Podcast"></category><category term="Space Junk"></category></entry></feed>